<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204393">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000584</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>304</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL029883-04</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000584</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transfusion-Transmitted Cytomegalovirus Prevention in Neonates</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the capacity of intravenously administered cytomegalovirus (CMV)-immune globin
      (CMVIG) to immunize high risk premature infants against CMV infections.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Premature infants who require multiple blood transfusions have a 15-30 percent incidence of
      cytomegalovirus infections. Many of these infections result in severe disease, with a
      mortality of about 20 percent. In theory, the infection could be avoided by using blood and
      blood products exclusively from CMV antibody negative donors. The use of such blood is
      impractical because it would require the rejection of approximately 40 percent of all blood
      donors. Studies had suggested that passively acquired antibody could reduce the incidence of
      disease in exposed neonates. This provided the rationale for the use of passive immunization
      with hyperimmune globin in premature infants likely to require multiple transfusions. Lots
      of high titer CMV immune globulin suitable for intravenous administration were prepared
      using a technique of screening outdated blood bank plasma for units with high levels of
      antibody to CMV.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized, double-blind. Subjects received either prophylactic CMVIG-intravenously or a
      placebo. Infants were followed for up to 12 weeks after discharge. Total sample size was
      expected to be 650.

      The study completion date listed in this record was inferred from last publication listed in
      the Citations section of this study record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1983</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1988</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Blood Transfusion</condition>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>immunoglobulins</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Neonates at high risk for transfusion-transmitted CMV infection. The neonates were either
        premature, of low birth weight, or had respiratory distress requiring the presence of an
        umbilical catheter.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>1 Year</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snydman DR. Prevention of cytomegalovirus-associated diseases with immunoglobulin. Transplant Proc. 1991 Jun;23(3 Suppl 3):131-5, discussion 135. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1648817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snydman DR, Werner BG, Meissner HC, Cheeseman SH, Schwab J, Bednarek F, Kennedy JL Jr, Herschel M, Magno A, Levin MJ, et al. Use of cytomegalovirus immunoglobulin in multiply transfused premature neonates. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 1995 Jan;14(1):34-40.</citation>
    <PMID>7715987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
