<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204428">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000549</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>93</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000549</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Estrogen Replacement and Atherosclerosis (ERA) in Older Women</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine if estrogen replacement therapy, with or without low dose progesterone, slows
      progression or induces regression of coronary atherosclerosis in postmenopausal women.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Cardiovascular disease is the number one cause of death in postmenopausal women.
      Postmenopausal estrogen replacement is associated with a lower incidence of cardiovascular
      disease in women, especially in those with established coronary artery disease. The strength
      of the apparent effect of estrogen in epidemiologic studies suggests that estrogen plays a
      fundamental role in the maintenance of vascular health. Animal data suggest that the current
      practice of adding the low dose progesterone to prevent endometrial hyperplasia may inhibit
      the beneficial effects of estrogen on coronary arteries. Before committing millions of
      postmenopausal women to long-term estrogen use for prevention of coronary artery disease, it
      is mandatory to demonstrate that it does indeed protect against coronary atherosclerosis, to
      determine the impact of co-treatment with progestin, and to understand the mechanisms
      through which estrogen may exert it's cardioprotective effects.

      The Office of Research on Women's Health provided $500,000 in Fiscal Year 1995 for
      recruitment of subjects.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized, placebo-controlled, blinded. The minimum diameter of coronary stenotic lesions
      was measured by angiography before and after three years in a group receiving unopposed
      estrogen replacement therapy, a group receiving estrogen replacement plus continuous low
      dose progestin, and a group receiving placebo. The incidence of clinical events was
      documented in all three groups. Secondary objectives of the trial included examining the
      effect of chronic and acute estrogen administration on endothelium-dependent coronary
      vasodilator capacity, plasma lipids and lipoproteins, antioxidant activity, blood pressure,
      glucose metabolism, and plasma hemostatic factors, as well as on behaviors, physical
      attributes, and psychosocial parameters. There were four pre-randomization variables in
      order to pre-stratify. These included current smoking status, insulin dependent diabetes,
      current lipid-lowering therapy, and the hospital where angiograms were performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1994</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 2000</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Postmenopause</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>estrogen replacement therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hormone replacement therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>estrogens</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>progestins</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Postmenopausal women with established coronary atherosclerosis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Herrington</last_name>
    <affiliation>Bowman Gray School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrington DM, Reboussin DM, Klein KP, Sharp PC, Shumaker SA, Snyder TE, Geisinger KR. The estrogen replacement and atherosclerosis (ERA) study: study design and baseline characteristics of the cohort. Control Clin Trials. 2000 Jun;21(3):257-85. Erratum in: Control Clin Trials 2000 Aug;21(4):414.</citation>
    <PMID>10822123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Folmar S, Oates-Williams F, Sharp P, Reboussin D, Smith J, Cheshire K, Macer J, Potvin Klein K, Herrington D. Recruitment of participants for the Estrogen Replacement and Atherosclerosis (ERA) trial. a comparison of costs, yields, and participant characteristics from community- and hospital-based recruitment strategies. Control Clin Trials. 2001 Feb;22(1):13-25.</citation>
    <PMID>11165419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrington DM, Reboussin DM, Brosnihan KB, Sharp PC, Shumaker SA, Snyder TE, Furberg CD, Kowalchuk GJ, Stuckey TD, Rogers WJ, Givens DH, Waters D. Effects of estrogen replacement on the progression of coronary-artery atherosclerosis. N Engl J Med. 2000 Aug 24;343(8):522-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10954759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erkkilä AT, Lichtenstein AH, Mozaffarian D, Herrington DM. Fish intake is associated with a reduced progression of coronary artery atherosclerosis in postmenopausal women with coronary artery disease. Am J Clin Nutr. 2004 Sep;80(3):626-32.</citation>
    <PMID>15321802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrington DM, Howard TD, Hawkins GA, Reboussin DM, Xu J, Zheng SL, Brosnihan KB, Meyers DA, Bleecker ER. Estrogen-receptor polymorphisms and effects of estrogen replacement on high-density lipoprotein cholesterol in women with coronary disease. N Engl J Med. 2002 Mar 28;346(13):967-74.</citation>
    <PMID>11919305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lakoski SG, Brosnihan B, Herrington DM. Hormone therapy, C-reactive protein, and progression of atherosclerosis: data from the Estrogen Replacement on Progression of Coronary Artery Atherosclerosis (ERA) trial. Am Heart J. 2005 Nov;150(5):907-11.</citation>
    <PMID>16290959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 3, 2006</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Estrogens</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
