<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204491">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000486</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000486</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Unstable Angina Pectoris Trial</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the efficacy of medical or surgical (coronary artery bypass graft) therapy with
      regard to survival and quality of life in patients with unstable angina and requisite
      coronary anatomy as defined by angiography.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Angina pectoris is a symptomatic condition of attacks of chest pain, often debilitating. It
      is caused by a decreased supply of blood to the heart, such as that which might occur in
      coronary artery disease. The usual treatment of angina pectoris is designed to relieve the
      symptoms. It includes avoidance of activities that produce the discomfort and the use of
      nitroglycerin and beta blocking drugs. Soon after the introduction of coronary bypass
      surgery, many doctors enthusiastically adopted this approach in treating patients with
      unstable angina.

      In 1972, emphasizing that there was no definitive evidence showing the superiority of
      intensive medical management or coronary bypass surgery in determining mortality and
      morbidity in patients hospitalized with unstable angina, some of the participating groups in
      the NHLBI Myocardial Infarction Research Units developed a cooperative clinical trial to
      compare these medical and surgical approaches to therapy.

      From 1972 through 1976, 288 patients were entered into this randomized clinical trial. One
      hundred forty-seven patients received intensive pharmacological medical therapy, and 141
      comparable patients underwent coronary artery bypass surgery. Careful follow-up studies were
      performed on patients in both groups, in-hospital and during the post-hospital phase. These
      studies included, apart from routine physical examinations, resting electrocardiograms,
      chest x-ray films, and grade exercise tolerance tests at six months and twelve months.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized, non-blind, sequential design with a control group and an experimental group. The
      patients in the experimental group were treated with coronary bypass surgery. Patients in
      the control group received intensive medical management. Endpoints were mortality and
      morbidity measures, such as incidence of myocardial infarction and persistence of angina.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1972</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1980</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Angina, Unstable</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>coronary artery bypass</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women, ages 21 to 65. Angina pectoris (class III or class IV) at rest or with
        minimal exercise.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lewis Becker</last_name>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adolph Hutter</last_name>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leon Resnekov</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Russell</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Schroeder</last_name>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Wallace</last_name>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Unstable angina pectoris: national cooperative study group to compare medical and surgical therapy. I. Report of protocol and patient population. Am J Cardiol. 1976 May;37(6):896-902.</citation>
    <PMID>1266755</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Unstable angina pectoris: national cooperative study group to compare surgical and medical therapy. III. Results in patients with S-T segment elevation during pain. Am J Cardiol. 1980 Apr;45(4):819-24.</citation>
    <PMID>6965816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Russell RO Jr, Wayne JB, Kronefeld J, Charles ED, Oberman A, Kouchoukos NT, White C, Rogers W, Mantle JA, Rackley CE. Surgical versus medical therapy for treatment of unstable angina: changes in work status and family income. Am J Cardiol. 1980 Jan;45(1):134-40.</citation>
    <PMID>6965333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2000</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Angina, Unstable</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
