<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204418">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000559</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>103</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000559</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's Estrogen/Progestin Lipid Lowering Hormone Atherosclerosis Regression Trial (WELL-HART)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the effects, in postmenopausal women, of hormone replacement therapy on
      progression/regression of coronary heart disease, as measured by quantitative angiography.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      The trial was a logical extension of preceding observational and cross-sectional studies on
      estrogen replacement therapy. Overall, the studies suggested a 50 percent reduction in risk
      of coronary heart disease in current estrogen users compared to non-users. In spite of such
      striking findings, most studies had been prone to a number of biases. One major criticism of
      observational studies had been that women receiving estrogen were generally healthier and
      more compliant than non-estrogen users.

      There was a very large body of observational data suggesting that the use of estrogen in
      postmenopausal women reduced coronary heart disease mortality by approximately 45 percent.
      At the same time, there had been some concern that replacement therapy increased the
      likelihood of uterine cancer and perhaps breast cancer as well, although it was generally
      accepted that this risk was probably significantly less than the benefits obtained from the
      reduction of coronary heart disease mortality.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled. After baseline angiograms, patients were
      randomized to one of three arms: micronized 17-beta estradiol, 1 milligram per day; 17-beta
      estradiol plus medroxyprogesterone, 5 milligrams per day for twelve days per month; and
      placebo. Subjects in all three arms received lipid-lowering therapy, low fat/low cholesterol
      diet, and the HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor, pravastatin, in sufficient dosage to reduce low
      density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol levels below 130 mg/dl. The primary endpoint was
      progression/regression of coronary obstructive disease as measured by angiography, including
      the expert human panel and quantitative computer analysis. The secondary endpoint was
      carotid media-intima thickness determined by ultrasound. Clinical measures included lipids,
      lipoproteins, apolipoproteins, estradiol and medroxyprogesterone levels, urinary prostanoid
      metabolites, and insulin/glucose metabolism. Subjects were recruited at three centers with
      active coronary angiography units. Several core facilities supported the study: a Core Lipid
      Lab, a Reproductive Endocrine Lab, the Biostatistics Lab (Data Coordinating Center) and the
      Angiographic Imaging Laboratory.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 2001</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Postmenopause</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>estrogen replacement therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hormone replacement therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>estradiol</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>medroxyprogesterone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Postmenopausal women with angiographically-documented coronary disease. Approximately 70
        percent minority
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Howard Hodis</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slater CC, Zhang C, Hodis HN, Mack WJ, Boostanfar R, Shoupe D, Paulson RJ, Stanczyk FZ. Comparison of estrogen and androgen levels after oral estrogen replacement therapy. J Reprod Med. 2001 Dec;46(12):1052-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11789085</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilcox JG, Hwang J, Hodis HN, Sevanian A, Stanczyk FZ, Lobo RA. Cardioprotective effects of individual conjugated equine estrogens through their possible modulation of insulin resistance and oxidation of low-density lipoprotein. Fertil Steril. 1997 Jan;67(1):57-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8986684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hodis HN, Mack WJ, Azen SP, Lobo RA, Shoupe D, Mahrer PR, Faxon DP, Cashin-Hemphill L, Sanmarco ME, French WJ, Shook TL, Gaarder TD, Mehra AO, Rabbani R, Sevanian A, Shil AB, Torres M, Vogelbach KH, Selzer RH; Women's Estrogen-Progestin Lipid-Lowering Hormone Atherosclerosis Regression Trial Research Group. Hormone therapy and the progression of coronary-artery atherosclerosis in postmenopausal women. N Engl J Med. 2003 Aug 7;349(6):535-45.</citation>
    <PMID>12904518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 23, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Estrogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
