<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204411">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>204</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Investigation of Pulmonary Embolism Diagnosis (PIOPED)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the sensitivity and specificity of two major, widely used technologies,
      radionuclear imaging (ventilation-perfusion scanning) and pulmonary angiography, for the
      diagnosis of pulmonary embolism.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      In 1983, reliable data on the incidence of pulmonary embolism in the adult population and in
      groups identified at risk were not available because the sensitivity and specificity of the
      diagnostic procedures had not been determined. Estimates suggested there were about half a
      million episodes of pulmonary embolism in hospitalized patients each year in the United
      States. Deaths attributable to pulmonary embolism would be expected in about one third of
      these patients if left untreated.

      The clinical diagnosis of pulmonary embolism was subject to a high frequency of false
      positives and false negatives. The most definitive diagnostic procedure was pulmonary
      angiography, an invasive, expensive procedure which was not without risk. It required
      specialized equipment and highly trained personnel both for performance and for
      interpretation. Therefore, it was used to diagnose pulmonary embolism only in the major
      medical centers. Another technique utilized as a method to diagnose pulmonary embolism
      involved a combination of perfusion and ventilation scanning; this method was only minimally
      invasive. A normal perfusion scan was thought to be of considerable value because it
      essentially excluded the diagnosis of pulmonary embolism. In selected patient populations,
      abnormal perfusion scans combined with normal ventilation scans were of substantial help in
      diagnosis.

      Although there had been no acceptable validation of the use of perfusion scans in the
      diagnosis of pulmonary embolism, thousands of patients had been evaluated for pulmonary
      embolism based on perfusion scanning often using methods of imaging now considered to be
      inadequate. In the early 1980s, clinical practice interpreted a negative perfusion scan as
      overwhelming evidence against the presence of pulmonary emboli. This interpretation had not
      been adequately tested either in a prospective study or by long-term follow-up of patients
      to determine clinical outcome. With regards to positive perfusion scans, there were data to
      suggest that as many as two-thirds of positive perfusion scans could not subsequently be
      confirmed by pulmonary angiography. Prospective studies in which timely angiograms using
      selective injections and improved imaging techniques were needed to evaluate the usefulness
      of positive perfusion scans.

      Phase I was initiated in September 1983. Protocols developed during Phase I underwent
      independent assessment review in April 1984 and were reviewed and approved by the May 1984
      National Heart, Lung, and Blood Advisory Council. Recruitment and intervention started in
      January 1985 and ended in September 1986. Follow-up was completed on September 30, 1987.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Patients suspected of pulmonary embolism underwent a ventilation-perfusion scan. Patients
      with an abnormal perfusion scan underwent angiography. All patients were followed for one
      year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1983</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 1989</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Embolism</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ventilation-perfusion ratio</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>angiography</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women suspected of having a pulmonary embolism and who met the criteria to undergo
        angiography.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Abass Alavi</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Greenspan</last_name>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Hales</last_name>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Herbert Saltzman</last_name>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Stein</last_name>
    <affiliation>Henry Ford Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Weg</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henry JW, Stein PD, Gottschalk A, Raskob GE. Pulmonary embolism among patients with a nearly normal ventilation/perfusion lung scan. Chest. 1996 Aug;110(2):395-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8697840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottschalk A, Stein PD, Henry JW, Relyea B. Can pulmonary angiography be limited to the most suspicious side if the contralateral side appears normal on the ventilation/perfusion lung scan? Data from PIOPED. Prospective Investigation of Pulmonary Embolism Diagnosis. Chest. 1996 Aug;110(2):392-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8697839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tissue plasminogen activator for the treatment of acute pulmonary embolism. A collaborative study by the PIOPED Investigators. Chest. 1990 Mar;97(3):528-33.</citation>
    <PMID>2106408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>PIOPED Investigators. Value of the ventilation/perfusion scan in acute pulmonary embolism. Results of the prospective investigation of pulmonary embolism diagnosis (PIOPED). JAMA. 1990 May 23-30;263(20):2753-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2332918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bone RC. Ventilation/perfusion scan in pulmonary embolism. 'The Emperor is incompletely attired'. JAMA. 1990 May 23-30;263(20):2794-5.</citation>
    <PMID>2185372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein PD, Gottschalk A, Saltzman HA, Terrin ML. Diagnosis of acute pulmonary embolism in the elderly. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1991 Nov 15;18(6):1452-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1939945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein PD, Alavi A, Gottschalk A, Hales CA, Saltzman HA, Vreim CE, Weg JG. Usefulness of noninvasive diagnostic tools for diagnosis of acute pulmonary embolism in patients with a normal chest radiograph. Am J Cardiol. 1991 May 15;67(13):1117-20.</citation>
    <PMID>2024602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein PD, Coleman RE, Gottschalk A, Saltzman HA, Terrin ML, Weg JG. Diagnostic utility of ventilation/perfusion lung scans in acute pulmonary embolism is not diminished by pre-existing cardiac or pulmonary disease. Chest. 1991 Sep;100(3):604-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1889240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein PD, Terrin ML, Hales CA, Palevsky HI, Saltzman HA, Thompson BT, Weg JG. Clinical, laboratory, roentgenographic, and electrocardiographic findings in patients with acute pulmonary embolism and no pre-existing cardiac or pulmonary disease. Chest. 1991 Sep;100(3):598-603.</citation>
    <PMID>1909617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein PD, Saltzman HA, Weg JG. Clinical characteristics of patients with acute pulmonary embolism. Am J Cardiol. 1991 Dec 15;68(17):1723-4.</citation>
    <PMID>1746481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein PD, Athanasoulis C, Greenspan RH, Henry JW. Relation of plain chest radiographic findings to pulmonary arterial pressure and arterial blood oxygen levels in patients with acute pulmonary embolism. Am J Cardiol. 1992 Feb 1;69(4):394-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1734655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quinn DA, Thompson BT, Terrin ML, Thrall JH, Athanasoulis CA, McKusick KA, Stein PD, Hales CA. A prospective investigation of pulmonary embolism in women and men. JAMA. 1992 Oct 7;268(13):1689-96.</citation>
    <PMID>1527878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2002</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 23, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
