<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204396">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000581</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>301</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>N01-HB-6-2970</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01-HB-6-2971</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01-HB-6-2972</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01-HB-6-2973</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000581</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Granulocyte Transfusion Study</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate granulocyte transfusion therapy with respect to its prophylactic and therapeutic
      effectiveness to prevent and aid recovery from infection. The study trials were conducted
      simultaneously.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Infection remains a major cause of death in patients receiving chemotherapy for malignant
      diseases. One approach to the problem of septicemia and high mortality in these patients was
      the therapeutic use of granulocyte transfusions. Improvements in collection techniques,
      employing continuous flow centrifugation, permitted the collection of granulocytes from a
      single, normal donor in sufficient numbers to study their application in the treatment of
      infections in granulocytopenic patients. Studies had demonstrated the efficacy of
      granulocyte transfusions as an adjunct in the therapy of septicemia due to gram negative
      microorganisms associated with granulocytopenia.

      The aims of the study were to determine (1) whether infections could be prevented in
      patients who received granulocytes prophylactically and (2) whether recovery from infection
      was aided in patients who received granulocytes therapeutically. Both trials utilized
      controls who received no granulocytes.

      Four contracts were awarded in September 1976. The protocol designed to evaluate the
      efficacy of prophylactic granulocyte transfusions was completed at the close of 1977. The
      protocol for the therapeutic trial was completed in April 1978. Approximately 90 patients
      were randomized in the prophylactic trial and 51 in the therapeutic trial. The Recruitment
      and Intervention Phase ended in February 1980. The trial has concluded.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Prophylactic Trial and Therapeutic Trial: randomized, non-blind, sequential. Eligible
      patients were randomized to daily granulocyte transfusions or no granulocyte transfusions.

      The study completion date listed in this record was inferred from the first publication
      listed in the Citations section of this study record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1976</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1981</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Blood Transfusion</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leukocyte transfusions</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Prophylactic Trial: males and females, 12 years or older, who were in the first induction
        phase of chemotherapy for acute leukemia, who had severe neutropenia, and who did not have
        documented infection.

        Therapeutic Trial: males and females, any
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Gale</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Geoffrey Herzig</last_name>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronald Strauss</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Iowa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strauss RG, Connett JE, Gale RP, Bloomfield CD, Herzig GP, McCullough J, Maguire LC, Winston DJ, Ho W, Stump DC, Miller WV, Koepke JA. A controlled trial of prophylactic granulocyte transfusions during initial induction chemotherapy for acute myelogenous leukemia. N Engl J Med. 1981 Sep 10;305(11):597-603.</citation>
    <PMID>6790985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winston DJ, Ho WG, Gale RP. Prophylactic granulocyte transfusions during chemotherapy of acute nonlymphocytic leukemia. Ann Intern Med. 1981 May;94(5):616-22.</citation>
    <PMID>6263139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2000</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
