<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204440">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>80</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stress Reduction &amp; CVD Morbidity and Mortality in Blacks</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the effects of two stress reduction techniques, Transcendental Meditation (TM)
      and Progressive Muscle Relaxation (PMR), on the control of mild hypertension in elderly
      Blacks with hypertension.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Life expectancy for Black Americans is about 10 percent less than for whites. The leading
      cause of excessive mortality in older Blacks is cardiovascular disease which may be largely
      due to disproportionately high rates of hypertension in older Blacks. Conventional
      antihypertensive drug therapies are frequently associated with adverse effects on
      quality-of-life (QL) and low compliance rates, especially in elderly minority populations.

      The present study is an extension of a pilot study on a comparable sample of 80 Black
      elderly. The previous study, which was the first of its kind, yielded results which
      indicated that both TM and PMR produced moderate reductions in systolic and diastolic blood
      pressure, with TM producing the most significant improvements in blood pressure and in
      quality-of-life. Dr. Schneider hypothesized from this and related evidence that TM should
      prove to be an effective therapeutic adjunct to regular pharmacotherapy for mild
      hypertension in elderly Blacks, and should prove even more effective in fostering compliance
      and in improving overall quality-of-life without any of the unpleasant side effects of
      anti-hypertensive medications.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized. Over an 18-month period, 213 people were screened for inclusion in the study. Of
      these, 127 with initial diastolic blood pressure of 90 to 109 mm Hg, systolic blood pressure
      of 189 mm Hg or less, and final baseline blood pressure of 179/104 or less mm Hg were
      randomized to treatment. Of the 127 participants, 16 did not complete follow-up blood
      pressure measurements. Thus, 111 subjects completed the study. All subjects were pretested
      over a four session baseline period on clinic blood pressure, ambulatory blood pressure,
      cardiovascular and emotional reactivity, and quality-of-life measures. Subjects were then
      randomly assigned, 36 to TM, 37 to PMR, and 38 to lifestyle modification education control
      and followed monthly with major post-tests at three months and eighteen months on these
      variables. The primary outcome variables were changes in clinic systolic and diastolic blood
      pressure values measured blindly. The secondary outcomes were changes in self-monitored home
      blood pressure and compliance.

      The study was extended through July, 2007 for an additional 5 years of followup of the
      cohort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1992</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>meditation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>relaxation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inner-city Blacks with mild hypertension
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Schneider</last_name>
    <affiliation>Maharishi International University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider RH, Staggers F, Alxander CN, Sheppard W, Rainforth M, Kondwani K, Smith S, King CG. A randomised controlled trial of stress reduction for hypertension in older African Americans. Hypertension. 1995 Nov;26(5):820-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7591024</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexander CN, Schneider RH, Staggers F, Sheppard W, Clayborne BM, Rainforth M, Salerno J, Kondwani K, Smith S, Walton KG, Egan B. Trial of stress reduction for hypertension in older African Americans. II. Sex and risk subgroup analysis. Hypertension. 1996 Aug;28(2):228-37.</citation>
    <PMID>8707387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barnes V, Schneider R, Alexander C, Staggers F. Stress, stress reduction, and hypertension in African Americans: an updated review. J Natl Med Assoc. 1997 Jul;89(7):464-76. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9220696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider RH, Alexander CN, Staggers F, Orme-Johnson DW, Rainforth M, Salerno JW, Sheppard W, Castillo-Richmond A, Barnes VA, Nidich SI. A randomized controlled trial of stress reduction in African Americans treated for hypertension for over one year. Am J Hypertens. 2005 Jan;18(1):88-98.</citation>
    <PMID>15691622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2008</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 23, 2008</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
