<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204608">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01MH045964</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH045964</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH045965</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH045966</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH045963</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DSIR AT-CT</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Panic Disorder: Long Term Strategies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Panic Disorder: Long Term Strategies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive behavior therapy (CBT) with or without medication has been used in the treatment
      of panic disorder (PD). The purpose of this study is 1) to determine whether nine months of
      maintenance cognitive-behavior therapy (CBT) significantly improves the likelihood of
      sustained improvement; and 2) to determine the acute acceptability and efficacy of
      medication therapy or continued CBT alone among patients who fail to respond sufficiently to
      an initial course of CBT alone.

      It has been found that patients with PD respond as well to CBT or medication alone as they
      do to a combination of the two. Since the combined treatments are expensive and CBT is
      associated with less risk of medical toxicity compared to medications, CBT alone will be
      used first.

      All patients will first receive CBT alone. If the patient responds to this therapy, the
      patient will be assigned randomly (like tossing a coin) to 1 of 2 groups. One group will
      continue to receive CBT (maintenance therapy) for 9 months. The other group of responders
      will not receive any further therapy. If a patient does not respond to CBT alone, he/she
      will be assigned randomly to 1 of 2 different groups. One group will receive paroxetine; the
      other will continue to receive CBT for a longer period. The response to treatment will be
      evaluated to see which regimen works best to treat PD. The study will last approximately 3
      years.

      An individual may be eligible for this study if he/she has panic disorder with no more than
      mild agoraphobia (fear of being in public places) and is at least 18 years old.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine if maintenance CBT produces a more sustained improvement among patients with
      panic disorder (PD) who respond to an initial course of cognitive behavior therapy (CBT)
      alone. For those who do not respond sufficiently to CBT alone, to determine if the addition
      of pharmacotherapy is acceptable and if this improves response among those inadequate
      responders to CBT alone.

      This multicenter study builds upon the findings of a prior study comparing imipramine,
      placebo, CBT, and their combination in the treatment of PD patients with no more than mild
      agoraphobia. That study found response rates were as high with CBT or imipramine alone as
      with their combination. Given the added cost of combined treatments, it therefore seems
      reasonable to begin with monotherapy. Further, following general principles of medical
      practice, it would be reasonable to initiate treatment with the less invasive cognitive
      behavioral intervention. It is then important to learn what should be done following initial
      treatment.

      All patients initially receive CBT alone. Patients are then randomized into 1 of 2
      post-acute studies, depending on response status. Responders are randomized to a maintenance
      study comparing no maintenance with 9 months of continued CBT. Nonresponders are randomized
      to a study comparing paroxetine with continued CBT. The following outcomes will be examined:
      the necessity of maintenance therapy in maintaining response; the ability of adjunct
      pharmacotherapy to improve the response of patients who did not respond to CBT alone;
      possible predictors of response and relapse; and possible mediators of response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2004</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Panic Disorder Severity Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and major assessment points plus monthly.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a 7-item scale providing ratings of core features of panic disorder and the degree of work and social impairment/interference due to the disorder.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impressions</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly, including all nonpretreatment major assessments.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Commonly used global rating of improvement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Albany Panic and Phobia Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>All major assessment points.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a 27-item scale consisting of three subscales that assess fear of agoraphobic situations, social situations, and situations and activities that produce bodily sensations commonly feared by individuals with panic disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety Sensitivity Index</measure>
    <time_frame>All major assessments and treatment visits.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a 16-item scale that assesses person's tendency to regard physiologic arousal as harmful.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Symptoms Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>All major assessment points</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is an individual's rating of the extent to which anxiety symptoms interfere with five areas of daily functioning: work, home management, private leisure, social leisure, and family relationships.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">379</enrollment>
  <condition>Panic Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Agoraphobia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive behavior therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paroxetine or other medication - algorithm used</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - primary diagnosis of Panic disorder with or without Agoraphobia (all levels of
        agoraphobia are included).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current substance abuse or dependence,

          -  current active suicidal potential;

          -  any history of psychosis, bipolar disorder (I or II) or cyclothymia;

          -  pending application or existing medical disability claim;

          -  significant cognitive impairment,

          -  current uncontrolled general medical illness requiring intervention,

          -  psychotherapy directed at anxiety or panic which will not be discontinued by the
             first treatment visit, and daily use of 2mg of Xanax or equivalent.

        Exclusion criteria for paroxetine study:

          -  hypersensitivity to Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors (SSRI),

          -  pregnancy, lactation, or planned pregnancy during the course of the study,

          -  contemporaneous medication that may interfere or interact with paroxetine,

          -  prior treatment with therapeutic doses of paroxetine (40mg/d for 1 mo),

          -  concurrent treatment with antidepressants.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katherine H. Shear, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David H Barlow, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston University Department of Psychology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jack Gorman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott Woods, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University, Department of Psychiatry, Anxiety Disorders Research Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston University, Department of Psychology, Center for Anxiety and Related Disorders</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hillside Hospital Phobia Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh, Department of Psychiatry, Panic, Anxiety and Traumatic Grief Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bu.edu/anxiety/</url>
    <description>Center for Anxiety and Related Disorders [Boston Study Site]</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://info.med.yale.edu/yfp/new/anxiety.html</url>
    <description>Yale Anxiety Disorders Research Clinic [New Haven Study site]</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barlow DH, Gorman JM, Shear MK, Woods SW. Cognitive-behavioral therapy, imipramine, or their combination for panic disorder: A randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2000 May 17;283(19):2529-36. Erratum in: JAMA 2000 Nov 15;284(19):2450. JAMA 2001 Nov 22-29;284(20):2597.</citation>
    <PMID>10815116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shear MK, Brown TA, Barlow DH, Money R, Sholomskas DE, Woods SW, Gorman JM, Papp LA. Multicenter collaborative panic disorder severity scale. Am J Psychiatry. 1997 Nov;154(11):1571-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9356566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gorman JM. A 28-year-old woman with panic disorder. JAMA. 2001 Jul 25;286(4):450-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11466124</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grilo CM, Money R, Barlow DH, Goddard AW, Gorman JM, Hofmann SG, Papp LA, Shear MK, Woods SW. Pretreatment patient factors predicting attrition from a multicenter randomized controlled treatment study for panic disorder. Compr Psychiatry. 1998 Nov-Dec;39(6):323-32.</citation>
    <PMID>9829138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huppert JD, Bufka LF, Barlow DH, Gorman JM, Shear MK, Woods SW. Therapists, therapist variables, and cognitive-behavioral therapy outcome in a multicenter trial for panic disorder. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2001 Oct;69(5):747-55.</citation>
    <PMID>11680551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hofmann SG, Barlow DH, Papp LA, Detweiler MF, Ray SE, Shear MK, Woods SW, Gorman JM. Pretreatment attrition in a comparative treatment outcome study on panic disorder. Am J Psychiatry. 1998 Jan;155(1):43-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9433337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 2, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Natalia A. Skritskaya, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Co-investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adult</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Long term treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Remission and relapse</keyword>
  <keyword>Male</keyword>
  <keyword>Panic Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Paroxetine</keyword>
  <keyword>Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Panic Disorder -- *therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Panic Disorder -- drug therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Paroxetine -- *therapeutic use</keyword>
  <keyword>Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors -- *therapeutic use</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Agoraphobia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Panic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Paroxetine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Therapeutic Uses</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
