<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204542">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P60AR030692</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIAMS-050</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Exercise on Older Persons With Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Exercise on Older Persons With Osteoarthritis (OA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Previous studies have found that exercise can reduce pain, improve endurance for physical
      activities, and improve cardiovascular fitness over time. However, these studies have not
      looked at the impact of exercise programs for older adults with osteoarthritis or at how
      long older adults continue exercising after a program is finished. This study will look at
      the long-term effects of a structured exercise program for people aged 60 or older who have
      osteoarthritis of the hip or knee. One goal of the exercise program is to encourage older
      people with osteoarthritis to continue exercising.

      We will randomly assign study participants to either the exercise program or a control group
      that does not do the exercise program. We will monitor participants at the start of the
      study, at 8 weeks, and every 3 months for 2 years after the program is completed. The
      exercise program lasts for 8 weeks and includes an exercise part and an educational part led
      by trained physical therapists. We believe that participants in the treatment (exercise)
      group will show higher rates of continued exercise and higher functional status over time
      compared to the group of people who do not participate in the exercise program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent exercise interventions have demonstrated statistically significant short-term
      improvements in muscle strength, fitness, and physical activity in people under the age of
      70. This study seeks to determine if those same benefits can be achieved in an older
      population (mean age 84) with osteoarthritis of the hip or knee. The study will examine the
      long-term effects of a structured exercise program that seeks to promote adherence to
      continued exercise.

      We will randomly assign people who meet the study criteria to the exercise intervention or
      control group. We will conduct measures at baseline, at 8 weeks, and at 3-month intervals
      for 2 years following the intervention. The exercise component of the intervention will
      include lower extremity muscle strengthening, range-of-motion exercises, and fitness
      walking. An educational component will focus on arthritis self-efficacy and perceived
      self-reported exercise efficacy. We hypothesize that treatment group participants will
      exhibit higher rates of adherence to exercise and higher functional status outcomes over
      time compared to controls.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 1983</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2003</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2003</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain and stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">217</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fit and Strong! is a multi-component exercise and health education program that incorporates flexibility, aerobic conditioning, strength training, and group discussion/problem solving for lifestyle change.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fit and Strong!</intervention_name>
    <description>Fit and Strong! is a multi-component exercise and health education program that includes flexibility, aerobic conditioning, strength training, and group discussion/problem solving for lifestyle change.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  60 years of age or older

          -  Presence of osteoarthritis of the lower extremities with an American College of
             Rheumatology functional class rating of I, II, or III

          -  No other contraindication from a personal physician for participation in the fitness
             walking

          -  Lack of moderate-to-severe cognitive impairment as assessed by the Short Portable
             Mental Status Questionnaire

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under 60 years of age

          -  Lack of osteoarthritis of the lower extremities

          -  Contraindication from a personal physician for participation in fitness walking

          -  Presence of moderate-to-severe cognitive impairment as assessed by the Short Portable
             Mental Status Questionnaire

          -  Steroid injections in either hip or knee within the previous 6 months

          -  Uncomplicated knee or hip surgery within previous year

          -  Complicated knee or hip surgery within previous year

          -  Plans for total knee or hip replacement within the next year

          -  Rheumatoid arthritis or other systemic inflammatory arthritis

          -  Diabetes that is not under control

          -  Current participation in a structured aerobic exercise program
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Hughes</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Research on Health and Aging</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bernard Horwich Jewish Community Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60659</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Park Village</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60646</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hughes SL, Seymour RB, Campbell R, Pollak N, Huber G, Sharma L. Impact of the fit and strong intervention on older adults with osteoarthritis. Gerontologist. 2004 Apr;44(2):217-28.</citation>
    <PMID>15075418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hughes SL, Seymour RB, Campbell RT, Huber G, Pollak N, Sharma L, Desai P. Long-term impact of Fit and Strong! on older adults with osteoarthritis. Gerontologist. 2006 Dec;46(6):801-14.</citation>
    <PMID>17169935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2007</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 20, 2007</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 21, 2000</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Susan Hughes</name_title>
    <organization>Center for Research on Health and Aging, UIC</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Health education</keyword>
  <keyword>Aerobic exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Self-efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle strength</keyword>
  <keyword>Outcomes research</keyword>
  <keyword>Longitudinal study</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
