<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204447">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000530</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>73</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000530</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Raynaud's Treatment Study (RTS)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the relative efficacy of usual medical care and a course of treatment by
      thermal biofeedback in reducing vasospastic attacks characteristic of Raynaud's syndrome.
      Also, to confirm the frequency and severity of attacks, examine the role of
      psychophysiological factors in precipitating attacks, and assess the influence of treatment
      on health quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Primary Raynaud's phenomenon is a peripheral vascular disorder resulting in vasospastic
      attacks provoked by cold and/or emotional stress. Attacks most often occur in the fingers,
      but may occur in other extremities as well.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized. Patients were assigned to one of four treatment groups: slow release Nifedipine,
      a calcium channel blocker; pill placebo; temperature biofeedback; or electromyograph
      biofeedback from the frontalis muscle. The primary endpoint was reduction in number of
      vasospastic attacks. Other endpoints included: other measures of Raynaud's attacks including
      frequency, severity, duration, response to laboratory-based cold challenge, and quality of
      life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1992</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 1998</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Raynaud's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nifedipine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>biofeedback (psychology)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>electromyography</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women with documented primary or secondary Raynaud's syndrome.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruce Thompson</last_name>
    <affiliation>Clinical Trials &amp; Surveys Corp (C-TASC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jennings JR, Maricq HR, Canner J, Thompson B, Freedman RR, Wise R, Kaufmann PG. A thermal vascular test for distinguishing between patients with Raynaud's phenomenon and healthy controls. Raynaud's Treatment Study Investigators. Health Psychol. 1999 Jul;18(4):421-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10431945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Comparison of sustained-release nifedipine and temperature biofeedback for treatment of primary Raynaud phenomenon. Results from a randomized clinical trial with 1-year follow-up. Arch Intern Med. 2000 Apr 24;160(8):1101-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10789602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown KM, Middaugh SJ, Haythornthwaite JA, Bielory L. The effects of stress, anxiety, and outdoor temperature on the frequency and severity of Raynaud's attacks: the Raynaud's Treatment Study. J Behav Med. 2001 Apr;24(2):137-53.</citation>
    <PMID>11392916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maricq HR, Jennings JR, Valter I, Frederick M, Thompson B, Smith EA, Hill R; Raynaud's Treatment Study Investigators. Evaluation of treatment efficacy of Raynaud phenomenon by digital blood pressure response to cooling. Raynaud's Treatment Study Investigators. Vasc Med. 2000;5(3):135-40.</citation>
    <PMID>11104295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Middaugh SJ, Haythornthwaite JA, Thompson B, Hill R, Brown KM, Freedman RR, Attanasio V, Jacob RG, Scheier M, Smith EA. The Raynaud's Treatment Study: biofeedback protocols and acquisition of temperature biofeedback skills. Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback. 2001 Dec;26(4):251-78.</citation>
    <PMID>11802676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2004</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 23, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Raynaud Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
