<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204496">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000481</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>71</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000481</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's Health Trial: Feasibility Study in Minority Populations</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the feasibility of recruiting women of different socioeconomic status and
      minority groups and to determine whether these women could achieve and maintain a modified
      fat-eating pattern. The full-scale trial sought to determine whether a low-fat diet could
      decrease the incidence of cancer and coronary heart disease in postmenopausal women. The
      National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute contributed funds over a three-year period to
      measure lipids, lipoproteins, and other cardiovascular disease risk factors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      The Request for Proposal for the Women's Health Trial: Feasibility Study in Minority
      Populations was developed and released by the National Cancer Institute with assistance from
      the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized. Recruitment began in August 1992 and ended in February 1994. Forty percent of
      the subjects were randomized to a control group and 60 percent to the dietary intervention
      group. Dietary counseling aimed to reduce total fat to 20 percent of calories, reduce
      saturated fat and dietary cholesterol intakes, and to increase the intake of fruits,
      vegetables, and grain products. Recruitment and randomization were conducted over an
      18-month period at three clinical centers. Other objectives of the trial included:
      development and evaluation of strategies for recruiting and retaining women of different
      racial and SES groups into a dietary intervention study; identification of factors affecting
      compliance; assessment of the effects of a modified fat eating pattern on cardiovascular
      disease risk factors, including fasting blood lipids and lipoproteins, glucose and insulin,
      body weight and blood pressure; identification and assessment of potential biochemical
      and/or biological markers for dietary adherence.

      Close-out visits began in May 1994 and ended in September 1994. These visits included six,
      twelve, and eighteen-month follow-up. NCI extended the coordinating center contract through
      January 1996 to support data analysis and publication of research results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1991</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 1996</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Postmenopause</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diet, fat-restricted</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Postmenopausal women, aged 50 to 69 years, who consumed 38 percent or more of total
        calories as fat at baseline.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Valerie George</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>W. Hall</last_name>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Albert Oberman</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowen D, Clifford CK, Coates R, Evans M, Feng Z, Fouad M, George V, Gerace T, Grizzle JE, Hall WD, Hearn M, Henderson M, Kestin M, Kristal A, Leary ET, Lewis CE, Oberman A, Prentice R, Raczynski J, Toivola B, Urban N. The Women's Health Trial Feasibility Study in Minority Populations: design and baseline descriptions. Ann Epidemiol. 1996 Nov;6(6):507-19.</citation>
    <PMID>8978881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coates RJ, Bowen DJ, Kristal AR, Feng Z, Oberman A, Hall WD, George V, Lewis CE, Kestin M, Davis M, Evans M, Grizzle JE, Clifford CK. The Women's Health Trial Feasibility Study in Minority Populations: changes in dietary intakes. Am J Epidemiol. 1999 Jun 15;149(12):1104-12.</citation>
    <PMID>10369504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristal AR, Feng Z, Coates RJ, Oberman A, George V. Associations of race/ethnicity, education, and dietary intervention with the validity and reliability of a food frequency questionnaire: the Women's Health Trial Feasibility Study in Minority Populations. Am J Epidemiol. 1997 Nov 15;146(10):856-69. Erratum in: Am J Epidemiol 1998 Oct 15;148(8):820.</citation>
    <PMID>9384206</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristal AR, Shattuck AL, Patterson RE. Differences in fat-related dietary patterns between black, Hispanic and White women: results from the Women's Health Trial Feasibility Study in Minority Populations. Public Health Nutr. 1999 Sep;2(3):253-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10512559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewis CE, George V, Fouad M, Porter V, Bowen D, Urban N. Recruitment strategies in the women's health trial: feasibility study in minority populations. WHT:FSMP Investigators Group. Women's Health Trial:Feasibility Study in Minority Populations. Control Clin Trials. 1998 Oct;19(5):461-76.</citation>
    <PMID>9741867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2001</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 23, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
