<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204453">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000524</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>43</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL034744-04</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000524</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Myocarditis Treatment Trial</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether immunosuppressive treatment improved cardiac function in patients with
      biopsy-proven myocarditis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Heart failure due to myocarditis can be a devastating illness. At the same time,
      immunosuppressive therapy is associated with considerable risks of untoward side effects.
      Clinicians did not know whether, under what circumstances, or in what form, this hazardous
      treatment should be used in such critically ill patients. In addition, if immunosuppressive
      therapy was of benefit, then endomyocardial biopsy in patients suspected of having
      myocarditis was a justified procedure. The trial also provided information concerning the
      side effects of immuno-suppressive therapy in such patients.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Patients were randomized into two treatment arms consisting of conventional therapy alone
      for congestive heart failure or combined with a twenty-four week regimen of
      immunosuppressive therapy. Immunosuppressive therapy consisted of prednisone with either
      cyclosporine or azathioprine. The primary outcome measure was a change in the left
      ventricular ejection fraction at twenty-eight weeks. Secondary endpoints included survival,
      failures of therapy, requirements for conventional therapy, assessments of symptoms,
      myocardial histology, and arrhythmias.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the Query/View/Report
      (QVR) System.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1986</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1994</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocarditis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cyclosporine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prednisone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women, 18 years of age or older, with left ventricular failure and
        biopsy-documented myocarditis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jay Mason</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mason JW, O'Connell JB. Clinical merit of endomyocardial biopsy. Circulation. 1989 May;79(5):971-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2653662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Connell JB, Mason JW. Diagnosing and treating active myocarditis. West J Med. 1989 Apr;150(4):431-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2660415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Connell JB, Mason JW. The applicability of results of streamlined trials to clinical practice: the Myocarditis Treatment Trial. Stat Med. 1990 Jan-Feb;9(1-2):193-6; discussion 196-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2345835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neumann DA, Burek CL, Baughman KL, Rose NR, Herskowitz A. Circulating heart-reactive antibodies in patients with myocarditis or cardiomyopathy. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1990 Nov;16(6):839-46.</citation>
    <PMID>2229805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mason JW, O'Connell JB, Herskowitz A, Rose NR, McManus BM, Billingham ME, Moon TE. A clinical trial of immunosuppressive therapy for myocarditis. The Myocarditis Treatment Trial Investigators. N Engl J Med. 1995 Aug 3;333(5):269-75.</citation>
    <PMID>7596370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hahn EA, Hartz VL, Moon TE, O'Connell JB, Herskowitz A, McManus BM, Mason JW. The Myocarditis Treatment Trial: design, methods and patients enrollment. Eur Heart J. 1995 Dec;16 Suppl O:162-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8682088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocarditis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
