<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204422">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>99</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000555</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's Angiographic Vitamin and Estrogen Trial (WAVE)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess whether hormonal replacement therapy and/or antioxidant treatment would stabilize
      or inhibit progression, and induce regression of coronary plaques. The mechanisms by which
      these treatments modified atherosclerosis in women were also explored.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Coronary artery disease is the leading cause of death in the United States, accounting for
      over 500,000 deaths each year. Although the onset of coronary artery disease is delayed in
      women, it is the single most important cause of death in women over the entire life span.
      Indeed, because more women than men survive to old age, mortality due to coronary artery
      disease for all ages combined is as great in women as in men. Furthermore, once they present
      with clinical evidence of coronary artery disease, women have a prognosis as poor as, or
      even worse, than that for men. In part, this may be due to late recognition of coronary
      artery disease in women, less intensive treatment of women, or a more adverse risk profile
      in women who develop coronary artery disease. The report of a recent Working Group on
      Angiographic Trials of Atherosclerosis Prevention notes that, compared to males, females who
      develop coronary artery disease, have various different characteristics which may affect the
      vascular response to lipid-altering interventions. These differences led the report to
      question whether the mechanisms and clinical benefits of lipid-altering agents may be
      different in men and women. It further noted that angiographic trials conducted to date have
      been based primarily upon the cholesterol-lowering treatments of diet or drugs and suggested
      that other approaches based upon the lipid hypothesis could profitably be tested and should
      be given the highest priority at this time; specifically recommended were trials of hormone
      replacement and antioxidant therapy in women.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Subjects were randomized into a 2 x 2 factorial trial of hormone replacement therapy and
      antioxidant therapy. Women were randomized into four treatment groups: both active hormone
      replacement and antioxidant; active hormone replacement therapy and antioxidant placebo;
      active antioxidant therapy and hormone replacement placebo; double placebo plus usual care.
      Hormone replacement therapy consisted of estrogen plus a progestin (PremPro) for all
      gynecologically intact women, and unopposed estrogen (Premarin) for women with
      hysterectomies. Antioxidants consisted of a combination of vitamin E and vitamin C.
      Angiographic change was a primary endpoint of this trial. The study was double-blind to the
      extent permitted by the interventions; however, it was fully-blinded with respect to outcome
      variables. Recruitment ended in August 1999. The mean duration of follow-up was
      approximately three years.

      The NHLBI awarded R01HL68397 in April 2001 as an ancillary study to WAVE. The study entitled
      &quot;Modifying Oxidative Damage in WAVE&quot; has its on site on this database.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 2003</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Postmenopause</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>estrogen replacement therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>estrogens, conjugated</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>progesterone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hormone replacement therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>supplementation, food</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ascorbic acid</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vitamin e</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Postmenopausal women, up to age 86, with angiographically documented coronary artery
        disease of at least 15 percent, but no more than 75 percent occlusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>38 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>86 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joel Verter</last_name>
    <affiliation>George Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waters DD, Alderman EL, Hsia J, Howard BV, Cobb FR, Rogers WJ, Ouyang P, Thompson P, Tardif JC, Higginson L, Bittner V, Steffes M, Gordon DJ, Proschan M, Younes N, Verter JI. Effects of hormone replacement therapy and antioxidant vitamin supplements on coronary atherosclerosis in postmenopausal women: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2002 Nov 20;288(19):2432-40.</citation>
    <PMID>12435256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsia J, Alderman EL, Verter JI, Rogers WJ, Thompson P, Howard BV, Cobb FR, Ouyang P, Tardif JC, Higginson L, Bittner V, Barofsky I, Steffes M, Gordon DJ, Proschan M, Younes N, Waters D. Women's angiographic vitamin and estrogen trial: design and methods. Control Clin Trials. 2002 Dec;23(6):708-27.</citation>
    <PMID>12505248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsia J, Bittner V, Tripputi M, Howard BV. Metabolic syndrome and coronary angiographic disease progression: the Women's Angiographic Vitamin &amp; Estrogen trial. Am Heart J. 2003 Sep;146(3):439-45.</citation>
    <PMID>12947360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howard BV, Hsia J, Ouyang P, Van Voorhees L, Lindsay J, Silverman A, Alderman EL, Tripputi M, Waters DD. Postmenopausal hormone therapy is associated with atherosclerosis progression in women with abnormal glucose tolerance. Circulation. 2004 Jul 13;110(2):201-6. Epub 2004 Jun 28.</citation>
    <PMID>15226212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levy AP, Friedenberg P, Lotan R, Ouyang P, Tripputi M, Higginson L, Cobb FR, Tardif JC, Bittner V, Howard BV. The effect of vitamin therapy on the progression of coronary artery atherosclerosis varies by haptoglobin type in postmenopausal women. Diabetes Care. 2004 Apr;27(4):925-30.</citation>
    <PMID>15047650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bittner V, Tripputi M, Hsia J, Gupta H, Steffes M; Women's Angiographic Vitamin &amp; Estrogen Investigators. Remnant-like lipoproteins, hormone therapy, and angiographic and clinical outcomes: the Women's Angiographic Vitamin &amp; Estrogen Trial. Am Heart J. 2004 Aug;148(2):293-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15308999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelemen M, Vaidya D, Waters DD, Howard BV, Cobb F, Younes N, Tripputti M, Ouyang P. Hormone therapy and antioxidant vitamins do not improve endothelial vasodilator function in postmenopausal women with established coronary artery disease: a substudy of the Women's Angiographic Vitamin and Estrogen (WAVE) trial. Atherosclerosis. 2005 Mar;179(1):193-200. Epub 2004 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>15721027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruo B, Tripputi MT, Hsue PY, Saigo M, Ouyang P, Waters DD. Usefulness of serum endothelin levels in predicting death and myocardial infarction but not coronary progression in postmenopausal women with coronary disease (from the Women's Angiographic Vitamin and Estrogen [WAVE] study). Am J Cardiol. 2005 Aug 1;96(3):335-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16054453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 8, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ascorbic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estrogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estrogens, Conjugated (USP)</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
