<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204482">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000495</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL021823</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000495</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Hypertension: A Randomized Trial</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether improved nutrition to correct overweight and high sodium intake, and
      regular frequent moderate rhythmic exercise to improve cardio-pulmonary fitness and to slow
      heart rate could lower blood pressure and prevent development of hypertension in
      hypertension-prone individuals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Diet modification is one of the strategies in the primary prevention of hypertension.
      Studies of the association between various factors and blood pressure in different
      populations have shown the occurrence of specific dietary factors associated with elevated
      blood pressures. The factors include overweight, alcohol consumption and high sodium intake.
      Heart rate is also an independent predictor of risk of hypertension. Diet and exercise are
      amenable to intervention to influence blood pressure with the aim of reducing the risk of
      developing hypertension.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      In the first phase of the trial participants were randomized to a Monitored (Control) Group
      or to an Intervention Group receiving individualized intervention to achieve changes in diet
      and physical activity. The goals of the Intervention Group were: a reduction of at least 10
      pounds or 5 percent of body weight for those above desirable weight; a reduction in daily
      sodium intake to 1800 mg; a modification of alcohol intake to no more than two drinks per
      day; and an increase in regular, moderate physical activity. The primary endpoint in the
      first phase of the trial was the comparison of mean blood pressure in the Intervention Group
      versus the Monitored Group. In the second phase of the trial, all randomized participants
      were followed for a minimum of five years. The primary endpoints in the second phase were
      the incidence of high blood pressure and/or hypertension.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 1978</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diet, reducing</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diet, sodium-restricted</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>alcohol restriction</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>exercise</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women, ages 30 to 44. Normal high blood pressure of 80-89 mm Hg.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stamler R, Stamler J, Gosch FC, McDonald AM. Primary prevention of hypertension--a randomized controlled trial. Ann Clin Res. 1984;16 Suppl 43:136-42.</citation>
    <PMID>6398983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stamler R, Stamler J, Gosch FC, Civinelli J, Fishman J, McKeever P, McDonald A, Dyer AR. Primary prevention of hypertension by nutritional-hygienic means. Final report of a randomized, controlled trial. JAMA. 1989 Oct 6;262(13):1801-7. Erratum in: JAMA 1989 Dec 8;262(22):3132.</citation>
    <PMID>2778913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2000</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
