<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204457">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000520</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>39</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL034545</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000520</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Coronary Aneurysms in Kawasaki Syndrome</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To test the efficacy of intravenous gamma globulin (IVGG) in preventing coronary artery
      aneurysms in children with Kawasaki Syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Kawasaki Syndrome is an acute febrile illness that occurs predominantly in previously
      healthy young children. It is of unknown etiology and was first described in Japan in 1967.
      The illness carries an acute mortality rate of approximately 3 percent. The Centers for
      Disease Control defines Kawasaki Syndrome as a fever lasting five or more days for which no
      explanation can be found. Patients also must have at least four of the following symptoms:
      bilateral conjunctival infection; infected or fissured lips, pharynx, or a 'strawberry
      tongue'; erythema of the palms or soles, or edema of the hands or feet, or generalized or
      periungual desquamation; rash; and cervical lymphadenopathy.

      Coronary artery aneurysms occur in 15-20 percent of children with the illness. In the past,
      no treatment had been shown to be effective in preventing this complication. Investigators
      in Japan began to use IVGG to reduce the aneurysm formation. Preliminary results showing the
      usefulness of this therapy led to a multicenter trial in Japan in which 400 mg/kg/day of
      IVGG were given for five days to children also receiving aspirin for the condition. Results
      of the Japanese trial showed that within 29 days of the onset of the disease, coronary
      artery dilatation had developed in 42 percent of the aspirin-treated children and in 15
      percent of the IVGG and aspirin-treated children.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Phase I was randomized, unblinded and stratified by age, sex, and center. Subjects were
      randomized to receive either 80 to 120 mg/kg/day of aspirin through day 14 of illness,
      subsequently reduced to 3 to 5 mg/kg/day as a single daily dose or to 400 mg/kg/day of
      intravenous gamma globulin for four consecutive days plus aspirin as above. Primary endpoint
      was formation of aneurysms as demonstrated by echocardiograms. Follow-up was for 7 weeks.

      Phase II of the trial began enrollment of 549 patients in May 1986 and ended enrollment in
      November 1989. Two hundred and seventy six children were randomized to receive 400 mg/kg of
      intravenous gamma globulin over four consecutive days. Two hundred and seventy-three
      received a single infusion of 2 g/kg of body weight over 10 hours. Both treatment groups
      received 100 mg/kg of aspirin per day through day 14 and then 3 to 5 mg/kg per day. The
      primary outcome variables were the presence or absence of coronary artery abnormalities
      evident at the two week and seven week follow-up examinations. Echocardiograms were obtained
      for 523 children at the two week visit and for 520 children at the seven week visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1985</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 1989</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Aneurysm</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Mucocutaneous Lymph Node Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>immunoglobulins, intravenous</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>aspirin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Boys and girls who met the CDC criteria for Kawasaki Syndrome. Subjects were excluded if
        they presented themselves to the participating centers after the tenth day of illness.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fred Rosen</last_name>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newburger JW, Takahashi M, Burns JC, Beiser AS, Chung KJ, Duffy CE, Glode MP, Mason WH, Reddy V, Sanders SP, et al. The treatment of Kawasaki syndrome with intravenous gamma globulin. N Engl J Med. 1986 Aug 7;315(6):341-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2426590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burns JC, Geha RS, Schneeberger EE, Newburger JW, Rosen FS, Glezen LS, Huang AS, Natale J, Leung DY. Polymerase activity in lymphocyte culture supernatants from patients with Kawasaki disease. Nature. 1986 Oct 30-Nov 5;323(6091):814-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2430187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shulman ST, Rowley AH. Does Kawasaki disease have a retroviral aetiology? Lancet. 1986 Sep 6;2(8506):545-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2427900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung DY, Geha RS, Newburger JW, Burns JC, Fiers W, Lapierre LA, Pober JS. Two monokines, interleukin 1 and tumor necrosis factor, render cultured vascular endothelial cells susceptible to lysis by antibodies circulating during Kawasaki syndrome. J Exp Med. 1986 Dec 1;164(6):1958-72.</citation>
    <PMID>3491174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burns JC, Wiggins JW Jr, Toews WH, Newburger JW, Leung DY, Wilson H, Glodé MP. Clinical spectrum of Kawasaki disease in infants younger than 6 months of age. J Pediatr. 1986 Nov;109(5):759-63.</citation>
    <PMID>3772656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gidding SS, Shulman ST, Ilbawi M, Crussi F, Duffy CE. Mucocutaneous lymph node syndrome (Kawasaki disease): delayed aortic and mitral insufficiency secondary to active valvulitis. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1986 Apr;7(4):894-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3958349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hicks RV, and Melish ME: Kawasaki Syndrome. In: Michael L. Miller (editor) The Pediatric Clinics of North American (Pediatric Rheumatology), pp. 1151-1175. W.B. Saunders Co., October 1986.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melish ME, and Hicks RV. Kawasaki Syndrome. In: John D. Nelson (editor) Current Therapy in Pediatric Infectious Disease, pp. 106-162. The C.V. Mosby Co., 1986.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takahashi M, Mason W, Lewis AB. Regression of coronary aneurysms in patients with Kawasaki syndrome. Circulation. 1987 Feb;75(2):387-94.</citation>
    <PMID>3802442</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung DY, Burns JC, Newburger JW, Geha RS. Reversal of lymphocyte activation in vivo in the Kawasaki syndrome by intravenous gammaglobulin. J Clin Invest. 1987 Feb;79(2):468-72.</citation>
    <PMID>2433307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowley AH, Gonzalez-Crussi F, Gidding SS, Duffy CE, Shulman ST. Incomplete Kawasaki disease with coronary artery involvement. Prog Clin Biol Res. 1987;250:357-65.</citation>
    <PMID>3423049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowley AH, Shulman ST. The search for the etiology of Kawasaki disease. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 1987 Jun;6(6):506-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3302905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gidding SS, Duffy CE, Pajcic S, Berdusis K, Shulman ST. Usefulness of echocardiographic evidence of pericardial effusion and mitral regurgitation during the acute stage in predicting development of coronary arterial aneurysms in the late stage of Kawasaki disease. Am J Cardiol. 1987 Jul 1;60(1):76-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3604947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowley AH, Shulman ST. Kawasaki disease: new etiologic clues and advances in therapy. Pediatr Dermatol. 1987 Aug;4(2):134-5.</citation>
    <PMID>3658834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowley AH, Gonzalez-Crussi F, Gidding SS, Duffy CE, Shulman ST. Incomplete Kawasaki disease with coronary artery involvement. J Pediatr. 1987 Mar;110(3):409-13.</citation>
    <PMID>3819942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowley AH, Shulman ST, Preble OT, Poiesz BJ, Ehrlich GD, Sullivan JR. Serum interferon concentrations and retroviral serology in Kawasaki syndrome. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 1988 Sep;7(9):663-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3140211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowley AH, Shulman ST. What is the status of intravenous gamma-globulin for Kawasaki syndrome in the United States and Canada? Pediatr Infect Dis J. 1988 Jul;7(7):463-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2457202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowley AH, Duffy CE, Shulman ST. Prevention of giant coronary artery aneurysms in Kawasaki disease by intravenous gamma globulin therapy. J Pediatr. 1988 Aug;113(2):290-4.</citation>
    <PMID>2456378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung DY, Cotran RS, Kurt-Jones E, Burns JC, Newburger JW, Pober JS. Endothelial cell activation and high interleukin-1 secretion in the pathogenesis of acute Kawasaki disease. Lancet. 1989 Dec 2;2(8675):1298-302.</citation>
    <PMID>2480498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newburger JW, Sanders SP, Burns JC, Parness IA, Beiser AS, Colan SD. Left ventricular contractility and function in Kawasaki syndrome. Effect of intravenous gamma-globulin. Circulation. 1989 Jun;79(6):1237-46.</citation>
    <PMID>2720925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burns JC, Huang AS, Newburger JW, Reinhart AL, Walsh MM, Hoch S, Leung DY. Characterization of the polymerase activity associated with cultured peripheral blood mononuclear cells from patients with Kawasaki disease. Pediatr Res. 1990 Feb;27(2):109-12.</citation>
    <PMID>1690383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newburger JW, Takahashi M, Beiser AS, Burns JC, Bastian J, Chung KJ, Colan SD, Duffy CE, Fulton DR, Glode MP, et al. A single intravenous infusion of gamma globulin as compared with four infusions in the treatment of acute Kawasaki syndrome. N Engl J Med. 1991 Jun 6;324(23):1633-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1709446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mucocutaneous Lymph Node Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins, Intravenous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rho(D) Immune Globulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
