<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204565">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000411</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>U01 AR45444 NIAMS-004B</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01AR045444</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000411</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Spine Patient Outcomes Research Trial (SPORT): Spinal Stenosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Spine Patient Outcomes Research Trial (SPORT): A Multicenter Trial for Spinal Stenosis (SpS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH/CDC)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Office of Research on Women's Health (ORWH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study tests the effectiveness of different treatments for the three most commonly
      diagnosed conditions of the lower backbone (lumbar spine). The purpose is to learn which of
      two commonly prescribed treatments (surgery and nonsurgical therapy) works better for
      specific types of low back pain. Low back pain is one of the most widely experienced health
      problems in the United States and the world. It is the second most frequent condition, after
      the common cold, for which people see a doctor or lose days from work.

      In this part of the study, we will treat patients with spinal stenosis (a narrowing of
      spaces in the backbone that results in pressure on the spinal cord and/or nerve roots) with
      a type of surgery known as posterior decompressive laminectomy or with nonsurgical methods.
      This study does not cover the cost of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Low back pain is considered one of the most widely experienced health problems in the U.S.
      and the world. It is the second most frequent condition, after the common cold, for which
      patients see a physician or lose days from work. Estimated costs to those who are severely
      disabled from low back pain range from $30-70 billion annually. Rates of spinal surgery in
      the U.S. have increased sharply over time, and researchers have documented 15-fold
      geographic variation in rates of these surgeries. In many cases, where one lives and who one
      sees for the condition appear to determine the rates of surgery. Despite these trends, there
      is little evidence proving the effectiveness of these therapies over non-surgical
      management.

      This study will use the National Spine Network to conduct a multicenter, randomized,
      controlled trial for the three most common diagnostic groups for which spine surgery is
      performed: lumbar intervertebral disc herniation (IDH), spinal stenosis (SpS), and spinal
      stenosis secondary to degenerative spondylolisthesis (DS). This arm of the trial will deal
      with patients from the second diagnostic group. The study will compare the most commonly
      used standard surgical treatments to the most commonly used standard nonsurgical treatments.
      We will conduct the study at 12 sites throughout the United States.

      The primary endpoint of the study will be changes in health-related quality of life as
      measured by the SF-36 health status questionnaire. Secondary endpoints will include patient
      satisfaction with treatment, utility for current health in order to estimate
      quality-adjusted life years (QALYS) as the measure for cost-effectiveness, resource use, and
      cost.

      We will follow patients at 6 weeks and 3, 6, 12, and 24 months to determine their health
      status, function, satisfaction, and health care use. We anticipate that we will enroll and
      randomly allocate a total of 370 study participants in this arm of the trial. We will track
      an additional observational cohort to assess health and resource outcomes. Enrollment in the
      Observational cohort has been completed as of February 2003.

      We will integrate data from the trial and observational cohorts to formally estimate the
      cost-effectiveness of surgical versus nonsurgical interventions for IDH, SpS, and DS. The
      results of this trial will provide, for the first time, scientific evidence as to the
      relative effectiveness of surgical versus nonsurgical treatment for these three most
      commonly diagnosed lumbar spine conditions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in health-related quality of life as measured by the SF-36 health status questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 wks, 3 and 6 mos, Annually thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 wks, 3 mos, Annually thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>utility for current health in order to estimate quality-adjusted life years (QALYS) as the measure for cost effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 yr, 4 yr</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>resource utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 wks, 3 and 6 mos, Annually thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cost</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 wks, 3 and 6 mos, Annually thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">289</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Decompressive laminectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-surgical treatments</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active physical therapy modality, Education/Counseling with home exercise instruction, and an NSAID if tolerated</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decompressive laminectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Removal of the hypertrophic inferior and superior articular facets will be performed when they are intruding upon the midline and causing both central and lateral recess stenosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-surgical treatments</intervention_name>
    <description>Active physical therapy modality, Education/Counseling with home exercise instruction, and an NSAID if tolerated</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-surgical treatments</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Duration of Symptoms: 12 or more weeks.

          -  Treatments tried: Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medical therapy and physical
             therapy.

          -  Surgical Screening: Pain in low back, buttocks, or lower extremity that becomes worse
             with lumbar extension. Must be confirmed by evidence of central or central-lateral
             compression of the cauda equina by a degenerative lesion of the facet joint, disc, or
             ligamentum flavum on MRI, computed tomography scans, or myelograms.

          -  Tests: MRI to confirm diagnosis and level(s).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous lumbar spine surgery.

          -  Not a surgical candidate for any of these reasons: Overall health that makes spinal
             surgery too life-threatening to be an appropriate alternative, patient has improved
             dramatically with conservative care, or the patient is unable (for any reason) to
             undergo surgery within 6 months.

          -  Possible pregnancy.

          -  Active malignancy: Patients with a history of any invasive malignancy (except
             nonmelanoma skin cancer) are ineligible unless they have been treated with curative
             intent AND have not had any clinical signs or symptoms of the malignancy for at least
             5 years.

          -  Current fracture, infection, and/or deformity (greater than 15 degrees of lumbar
             scoliosis, using Cobb measure technique) of the spine.

          -  Age less than 18 years.

          -  Cauda equina syndrome or progressive neurologic deficit (usually requiring urgent
             surgery).

          -  Unavailability for followup (planning to move, no telephone, etc.) or inability to
             complete data surveys.

          -  Symptoms less than 12 weeks.

          -  Patient currently enrolled in any experimental &quot;spine related&quot; study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James N. Weinstein, DO, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Spine Care Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco (UCSF)</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143-0728</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University, The Emory Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush-Presbyterian, St. Luke's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612-3833</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maine Spine &amp; Rehabilitation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scarborough</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04074</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>William Beaumont Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Royal Oak</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48073-9952</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nebraska Foundation for Spinal Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68154-4438</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center - Spine Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital for Special Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University, The Hospital for Joint Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Western Reserve University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rothman Institute at Thomas Jefferson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107-4216</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://sport.dartmouth.edu/nsn</url>
    <description>Click here to view the Spine Patient Outcomes Research Trial (SPORT) Web site.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birkmeyer NJ, Weinstein JN, Tosteson AN, Tosteson TD, Skinner JS, Lurie JD, Deyo R, Wennberg JE. Design of the Spine Patient outcomes Research Trial (SPORT). Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2002 Jun 15;27(12):1361-72.</citation>
    <PMID>12065987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinstein JN, Brown PW, Hanscom B, Walsh T, Nelson EC. Designing an ambulatory clinical practice for outcomes improvement: from vision to reality--the Spine Center at Dartmouth-Hitchcock, year one. Qual Manag Health Care. 2000 Winter;8(2):1-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10787504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fanciullo GJ, Hanscom B, Weinstein JN, Chawarski MC, Jamison RN, Baird JC. Cluster analysis classification of SF-36 profiles for patients with spinal pain. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2003 Oct 1;28(19):2276-82.</citation>
    <PMID>14520044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lurie JD, Birkmeyer NJ, Weinstein JN. Rates of advanced spinal imaging and spine surgery. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2003 Mar 15;28(6):616-20.</citation>
    <PMID>12642771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walsh TL, Hanscom B, Lurie JD, Weinstein JN. Is a condition-specific instrument for patients with low back pain/leg symptoms really necessary? The responsiveness of the Oswestry Disability Index, MODEMS, and the SF-36. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2003 Mar 15;28(6):607-15.</citation>
    <PMID>12642770</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Weinstein JN, Tosteson TD, Lurie JD, Tosteson AN, Blood E, Hanscom B, Herkowitz H, Cammisa F, Albert T, Boden SD, Hilibrand A, Goldberg H, Berven S, An H; SPORT Investigators. Surgical versus nonsurgical therapy for lumbar spinal stenosis. N Engl J Med. 2008 Feb 21;358(8):794-810. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0707136.</citation>
    <PMID>18287602</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Weinstein JN, Tosteson TD, Lurie JD, Tosteson A, Blood E, Herkowitz H, Cammisa F, Albert T, Boden SD, Hilibrand A, Goldberg H, Berven S, An H. Surgical versus nonoperative treatment for lumbar spinal stenosis four-year results of the Spine Patient Outcomes Research Trial. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2010 Jun 15;35(14):1329-38. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e3181e0f04d.</citation>
    <PMID>20453723</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tosteson AN, Lurie JD, Tosteson TD, Skinner JS, Herkowitz H, Albert T, Boden SD, Bridwell K, Longley M, Andersson GB, Blood EA, Grove MR, Weinstein JN; SPORT Investigators. Surgical treatment of spinal stenosis with and without degenerative spondylolisthesis: cost-effectiveness after 2 years. Ann Intern Med. 2008 Dec 16;149(12):845-53.</citation>
    <PMID>19075203</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tosteson AN, Tosteson TD, Lurie JD, Abdu W, Herkowitz H, Andersson G, Albert T, Bridwell K, Zhao W, Grove MR, Weinstein MC, Weinstein JN. Comparative effectiveness evidence from the spine patient outcomes research trial: surgical versus nonoperative care for spinal stenosis, degenerative spondylolisthesis, and intervertebral disc herniation. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2011 Nov 15;36(24):2061-8. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e318235457b.</citation>
    <PMID>22048651</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 3, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 3, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spinal stenosis (SpS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervertebral disc herniation (IDH)</keyword>
  <keyword>Degenerative spondylolisthesis (DS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Low back pain (LBP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonsurgical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized study</keyword>
  <keyword>Multicenter</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
