<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204395">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>302</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000582</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cooperative Study of Factor VIII Inhibitors</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To test the efficacy of prothrombin complex concentrates (Factor IX) in the treatment of
      hemophiliac patients who had inhibitors to Factor VIII.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Despite major advances in the treatment of patients with hemophilia, a serious remaining
      challenge was presented by the occurrence of circulating inhibitors to Factor VIII. Because
      of lack of information on the natural course of patients with Factor VIII inhibitors, the
      relative efficacy of various modes of therapy was not established. The Division of Blood
      Diseases and Resources decided to sponsor a clinical investigation which would evaluate
      populations of hemophilia patients for Factor VIII inhibitors, follow up these patients to
      provide information on the natural history of the inhibitor in the hemophilia patients, and
      make available a reference center to monitor results and attain uniformity.

      Treatment of a patient with a severe inhibitor and consequent bleeding remained a problem.
      Management included protracted treatment with Factor VIII, use of immunosuppressive agents
      and prothrombin complex (or Factor IX) concentrates. The rationale for Factor IX was that it
      bypassed the defect in Factor VIII caused by the inhibitor. This method of therapy attracted
      wide popularity, but the success was greatly debated. It was intended at the very outset of
      the Factor VIII study that therapeutic trials involving patients with inhibitors would not
      be a prime function, but that such studies would be monitored if necessary. A controlled
      trial of Factor IX concentrates therapy was strongly advised by the DBDR Advisory Committee.
      Accordingly, during fiscal year 1978, a protocol for a double-blind control study was
      developed by the Factor VIII inhibitor group. The trial began in the spring of 1978, and the
      intervention terminated about one year later.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Double-blind study; patients served as their own controls. A total of 51 patients each
      received a single large dose of Konyne, Proplex, or diluted albumin (as a control). Joint
      bleeding of the elbow, knee, and ankle was evaluated six hours after each dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1978</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 1979</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Blood Coagulation Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Hematologic Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hemophilia A</condition>
  <condition>Hemorrhagic Disorders</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>factor ix</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Males with hemophilia, not stratified as to ethnic group.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Louis Aledort</last_name>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J. Edson</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>M. Eyster</last_name>
    <affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott Goodnight</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Oregon Health Sciences Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Hathaway</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jack Lazerson</last_name>
    <affiliation>Milwaukee Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Levine</last_name>
    <affiliation>Memorial hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeanne Lusher</last_name>
    <affiliation>Wayne State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Campbell McMillan</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandor Shapiro</last_name>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eyster ME, Gill FM, Blatt PM, Hilgartner MW, Ballard JO, Kinney TR. Central nervous system bleeding in hemophiliacs. Blood. 1978 Jun;51(6):1179-88.</citation>
    <PMID>647123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lusher JM, McMillan CW. Severe factor VIII and factor IX deficiency in females. Am J Med. 1978 Oct;65(4):637-48.</citation>
    <PMID>309282</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kasper CK. Effect of prothrombin complex concentrates on factor VIII inhibitor levels. Blood. 1979 Dec;54(6):1358-68.</citation>
    <PMID>508942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lusher JM, Shapiro SS, Palascak JE, Rao AV, Levine PH, Blatt PM. Efficacy of prothrombin-complex concentrates in hemophiliacs with antibodies to factor VIII: a multicenter therapeutic trial. N Engl J Med. 1980 Aug 21;303(8):421-5.</citation>
    <PMID>6771653</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerety RJ, Eyster ME, Tabor E, Drucker JA, Lusch CJ, Prager D, Rice SA, Bowman HS. Hepatitis B virus, hepatitis A virus and persistently elevated aminotransferases in hemophiliacs. J Med Virol. 1980;6(2):111-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6264019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 26, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Blood Coagulation Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemophilia A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhagic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemostatic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
