<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204375">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000602</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>315</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000602</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Hydroxyurea in Sickle Cell Anemia (PED HUG)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether hydroxyurea prevents the onset of chronic end organ damage in young
      children with sickle cell anemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Sickle cell anemia is a complex syndrome with multiple organ system disturbances brought
      about by the interplay of genetic, humoral, vascular and environmental factors. The clinical
      course can be one of abrupt and insidious exacerbations and remissions, often migratory and
      repetitive. These events may result in impairment of function, permanently damaged organs,
      and ultimately death. Although there is wide variability in the clinical expression of
      sickle cell disease, this complex set of clinical manifestations is experienced by most
      patients. In addition, there is no evidence that the primary disease process is different in
      children when compared with adults with regard to painful episodes. However, children have a
      higher incidence of respiratory viral infections, and are susceptible to pneumococcal
      septicemia. With the successful completion of the Multicenter Study of Hydroxyurea (MSH)
      Trial in adults, attention has now been focused on the use of this agent in children.

      The Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease (CSSCD) has demonstrated that sickle cell
      anemia patients with increased painful episode rates die at a younger age. In addition,
      increased levels of fetal hemoglobin are associated with improved survival, and is probably
      a reliable childhood forecaster of adult life expectancy. The beneficial effect produced by
      hydroxyurea is thought to occur because it increases fetal hemoglobin levels. Therefore, if
      chronic end organ damage can be prevented in early childhood by hydroxyurea administration,
      and if the crisis rate can be decreased by hydroxyurea use early in life, sickle cell anemia
      patients may experience increased longevity and an improved quality of life.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The Phase I-Phase II study, HUG-KIDS, examined the safety of hydroxyurea. Children with
      sickle cell anemia, age 5 to 15 years, were eligible for this multicenter Phase I/II trial.
      Hydroxyurea was started at 15 mg/kg/d and escalated to 30 mg/kg/d unless the patient
      experienced laboratory toxicity. Patients were monitored by 2-week visits to assess
      compliance, toxicity, clinical adverse events, growth parameters, and laboratory efficacy
      associated with hydroxyurea treatment. Eighty-four children were enrolled between December
      1994 and March 1996. Sixty-eight children reached maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and 52 were
      treated at MTD for 1 year. The study was conducted at four Comprehensive Sickle Cell Centers
      by the following investigators: Thomas R. Kinney at Duke University Medical Center, Durham,
      North Carolina; Kwaku Ohene-Frempong at Children's Hospital of Philadelphia; Orah S. Platt
      at Children's Hospital in Boston; and Elliot Vichinsky at Children's Hospital in Oakland,
      California. The complete study lasted three years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 1994</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 1997</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Anemia, Sickle Cell</condition>
  <condition>Hematologic Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hemoglobinopathies</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Children with sickle cell disease and between the ages of five and eighteen years.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phase I/II Multicenter Pediatric Trial of Hydroxyurea (HUG-Kids). Blood, 90 (Suppl 1):Abstract # 1974, 1997.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kinney TR, Helms RW, O'Branski EE, Ohene-Frempong K, Wang W, Daeschner C, Vichinsky E, Redding-Lallinger R, Gee B, Platt OS, Ware RE. Safety of hydroxyurea in children with sickle cell anemia: results of the HUG-KIDS study, a phase I/II trial. Pediatric Hydroxyurea Group. Blood. 1999 Sep 1;94(5):1550-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10477679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang WC, Helms RW, Lynn HS, Redding-Lallinger R, Gee BE, Ohene-Frempong K, Smith-Whitley K, Waclawiw MA, Vichinsky EP, Styles LA, Ware RE, Kinney TR. Effect of hydroxyurea on growth in children with sickle cell anemia: results of the HUG-KIDS Study. J Pediatr. 2002 Feb;140(2):225-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11865275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 26, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemoglobinopathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyurea</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
