<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204560">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000416</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P60AR020613</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P60AR020613</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NIAMS-012</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EEHRS Project 3</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000416</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Arthritis-Related Work Disability</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevention of Arthritis-Related Work Disability: A Trial of Job Retention Services Provided to Employed Persons With Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People with rheumatic disorders (arthritis) often have trouble keeping their jobs. This
      study will look at whether vocational rehabilitation (VR) will improve the ability of
      employed people with arthritis to keep their jobs. Job retention VR services target key
      factors that increase the risk of job loss. They aim to modify jobs to reduce barriers
      caused by functional limitations and disease symptoms, future career planning, and establish
      a partnership with a VR counselor for ongoing help.

      We will conduct the study among patients with rheumatic disorders recruited in eastern
      Massachusetts. We will give 120 study participants job retention services provided by VR
      counselors. We will give another 120 participants literature about employment- related
      resources. We will compare the outcomes of the two groups to evaluate the usefulness of job
      retention services in preventing job loss in people with rheumatic disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Job loss commonly occurs among people with rheumatic disorders. This study will determine
      whether vocational rehabilitation (VR) provided to employed people with rheumatic disorders
      will improve their ability to remain employed. VR is applied primarily to people who have
      already lost their jobs. However, using job retention VR services may prevent, or delay, the
      onset of employment work loss among people with rheumatic disorders. Job retention VR
      services target important employment-loss risk factors. They do so by modifying jobs to
      reduce barriers posed by functional limitations and symptoms, promoting future career
      planning, and establishing an alliance with a VR counselor for ongoing assistance.

      The study is a randomized, controlled trial conducted among patients with rheumatic
      disorders recruited from the practices of rheumatologists in eastern Massachusetts.

      We will randomly assign 120 study participants to receive job-retention services provided by
      VR counselors and 120 participants (controls) to receive literature about employment-related
      resources. We will assess intermediate outcome variables (self-efficacy, work limitations,
      and job accommodation-seeking behaviors) and the endpoint outcome variable, work instability
      (a measure that includes employment loss), immediately prior to the interventions and at
      6-month intervals over a 24-month period after the interventions are carried out. We will
      compare the outcomes of the two groups to evaluate the usefulness of job retention services
      in forestalling work instability in this population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2001</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2001</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>job losses</measure>
    <time_frame>every 6 months for up to 42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Periods of work cessation of at least 6 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>limitation in ability to work</measure>
    <time_frame>every 6 months for up to 42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Extent of on the job limitation due to health condition as measured by the Work Limitations Questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">242</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <condition>Ankylosing Spondylitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rehabilitation counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rehabilitation counseling
Experimental
Rehabilitation counseling was provided by rehabilitation counselors. They administered the Work Experience Survey; provided and discussed disability rights and responsibilities and provided career counseling they as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>printed information</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active comparator
Control group participants received relevant printed information in the mail only; no rehabilitation counseling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rehabilitation counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Provided in 2 in-person meetings and in follow-up phone calls</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehabilitation counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>printed information</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must currently be employed full or part time

          -  Must live in selected communities in eastern Massachusetts

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Plans to move from area

          -  Plans to have joint replacement surgery in next 6 months

          -  Plans to retire or go on disability within next 2 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Saralynn J. Allaire, Sc.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allaire SH, Li W, LaValley,M: Work Problems reported by employed persons with reheumatic diseases and their association with work satisfaction. Arthritis Rheumatic 43:S128,2000</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allaire SH, Li W, LaValley, M. Can job retention vocational rehabilitation services reduce work disability among employed persons with rheumatic diseases? Arthritis Rheum 44 (supplement):S813, 2001.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allaire SH. Update on work disability in rheumatic diseases. Curr Opin Rheumatol. 2001 Mar;13(2):93-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11224732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Buck PD, Schoones JW, Allaire SH, Vliet Vlieland TP. Vocational rehabilitation in patients with chronic rheumatic diseases: a systematic literature review. Semin Arthritis Rheum. 2002 Dec;32(3):196-203. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12528084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Allaire SH, Li W, LaValley MP. Reduction of job loss in persons with rheumatic diseases receiving vocational rehabilitation: a randomized controlled trial. Arthritis Rheum. 2003 Nov;48(11):3212-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14613285</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Allaire SH, Niu J, Lavalley MP. Employment and Satisfaction Outcomes From a Job Retention Intervention Delivered to Persons with Chronic Diseases. Rehabilitation Counseling Bulletin 48(2):100-109, 2005</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 31, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 3, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Saralynn J. Allaire</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Rheumatic disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Work-related disability</keyword>
  <keyword>Vocational rehabilitation (VR)</keyword>
  <keyword>Job retention services</keyword>
  <keyword>Work limitations</keyword>
  <keyword>Work instability</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lupus Erythematosus, Systemic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spondylitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spondylitis, Ankylosing</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
