<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204470">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000507</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>26</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000507</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intravenous Streptokinase in Acute Myocardial Infarction</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether the administration of intravenous streptokinase (SK) early in the
      course of acute, transmural myocardial infarction would limit myocardial damage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Determination of the potential value of thrombolytic therapy in patients with acute
      myocardial infarction was an issue of major importance in 1983. An estimated 1.4 million
      heart attacks occurred each year, of which over 500,000 were fatal. Reduction of mortality
      required an effective means to reduce infarct size. Studies indicated that reperfusion
      represented a potent means of achieving salvage of ischemic myocardium. Pilot clinical
      studies indicated that reperfusion could be achieved in a substantial percentage of patients
      by lysis of coronary thrombosis with both intracoronary and intravenous streptokinase
      administration. Intracoronary thrombolysis was receiving widespread clinical applications
      but had many limitations. The intracoronary route took 90-120 minutes longer to administer
      than the intravenous route. Because intracoronary therapy required the availability of a
      catheterization laboratories and highly skilled invasive cardiologists, this treatment was
      not available to large numbers of patients who were hospitalized in smaller community
      hospitals.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Randomized design with two groups and fixed sample size. Control patients received routine
      coronary care. The treatment group received intravenous streptokinase plus conventional
      care. This was followed with intravenous heparin and warfarin. The primary endpoint was 14
      day mortality. Secondary endpoints included angiographic patency of the involved coronary
      artery at 10 to 14 days, left ventricular function, segmental wall motion analysis, and
      myocardial infarction size at 30-45 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1983</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 1994</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>streptokinase</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women, aged less than 75. Myocardial infarction onset within six hours.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin GV, Sheehan FH, Stadius M, Maynard C, Davis KB, Ritchie JL, Kennedy JW. Intravenous streptokinase for acute myocardial infarction. Effects on global and regional systolic function. Circulation. 1988 Aug;78(2):258-66.</citation>
    <PMID>3396164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ritchie JL, Cerqueira M, Maynard C, Davis K, Kennedy JW. Ventricular function and infarct size: the Western Washington Intravenous Streptokinase in Myocardial Infarction Trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1988 Apr;11(4):689-97.</citation>
    <PMID>3280640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kennedy JW, Martin GV, Davis KB, Maynard C, Stadius M, Sheehan FH, Ritchie JL. The Western Washington Intravenous Streptokinase in Acute Myocardial Infarction Randomized Trial. Circulation. 1988 Feb;77(2):345-52. Erratum in: Circulation 1988 May;77(5):1037.</citation>
    <PMID>3276409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 1994</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 23, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Streptokinase</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
