<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204824">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000135</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-34</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000135</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Studies of the Ocular Complications of AIDS (SOCA)--Monoclonal Antibody CMV Retinitis Trial (MACRT)</brief_title>
  <acronym>MACRT</acronym>
  <official_title>Monoclonal Antibody CMV Retinitis Trial (MACRT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the efficacy and safety of a human anti-CMV monoclonal antibody, MSL-109, as
      adjunct therapy for controlling CMV retinitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CMV retinitis is the most common intraocular infection in patients with AIDS and is
      estimated to affect 35 to 40 percent of patients with AIDS. Untreated CMV retinitis is a
      progressive disorder, the end result of which is total retinal destruction and blindness. As
      of September 1996, drugs approved by the United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
      for the treatment of CMV retinitis were ganciclovir (Cytovene), foscarnet (Foscavir), and
      cidofovir (Vistide). All systemically administered anti-CMV drugs are given in a similar
      fashion consisting of initial 2-week high-dose treatment (induction) to control the
      infection followed by long-term lower dose treatment (maintenance) to prevent relapse.
      Ganciclovir is available in both intravenous and oral formulations, foscarnet only in an
      intravenous formulation, and cidofovir is given by intermittent intravenous administration.
      A surgically implanted intraocular sustained-release ganciclovir device (Vitrasert) is also
      approved by the FDA for the treatment of CMV retinitis.

      Despite the use of continuous maintenance therapy, given enough time, all patients with CMV
      retinitis on systemically administered drugs relapse. Preliminary studies suggested that the
      anti-CMV monoclonal antibody, MSL-109, when administered in conjunction with ganciclovir,
      markedly prolonged the time to relapse. Therefore, a randomized controlled clinical trial
      evaluating MSL-109 as adjunct therapy was conducted.

      The MACRT was a randomized, placebo-controlled, multicenter clinical trial evaluating the
      efficacy and safety of MSL-109 as adjunct therapy for the treatment of CMV retinitis.
      Patients with CMV retinitis, both those newly diagnosed and those suffering a relapse with
      active retinitis, were eligible. Primary therapy (e.g., ganciclovir, foscarnet, etc.) was
      determined by the treating local physician. The patients enrolled in the trial were
      randomized to either MSL-109 or placebo, administered as a rapid intravenous infusion every
      2 weeks. Outcomes included survival, retinitis progression, change in amount of retinal area
      involved by CMV, loss of visual function (acuity and field), and morbidity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1996</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 1996</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>All patients enrolled were followed for a 17 month period or until a common study closing date</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>to evaluate the efficacy of an intravenous human monoclonal antibody to cytomegalovirus (CMV), MSL-109, as adjuvant treatment for CMV retinitis. .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">209</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSL-109</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The dose MSL-109 administered by intravenous infusion every 2 weeks 60 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo administered intravenous infusion every 2 weeks 60 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MSL-109</intervention_name>
    <description>60 mg, IV (in vein) every two weeks, treatment continued until death or common closeout.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSL-109</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Monoclonal antibodies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>60 mg, IV (in vein) every two weeks, treatment continued until death or common closeout.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  13 years or older at entry

          -  Diagnosis of AIDS according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)
             definition

          -  Diagnosis of active CMV retinitis as determined by a SOCA-certified ophthalmologist
             at time of enrollment

          -  At least one lesion whose size is one-quarter or more optic disc area

          -  Currently receiving (for relapsed patients) or scheduled to receive (for newly
             diagnosed patients) drugs for primary treatment of CMV retinitis that are not
             contraindicated for use with MSL-109

          -  Visual acuity, in at least one eye that meets other eligibility criteria, of 3 or
             more letters on ETDRS chart at 1 meter distance (Snellen equivalent 5/200). Patients
             with poorer visual acuity may be enrolled if the visual acuity impairment is possibly
             reversible (eg, due to optic disc edema) and vision is at least light perception in
             that eye

          -  Karnofsky score of 60 or more

          -  Willingness and ability, with the assistance of a caregiver if necessary, to comply
             with treatment and follow up procedures

          -  signed consent statement

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Current treatment with intravenous immune globulin (IVIG), CMV immune globulin
             (CMVIG), alpha-interferon (alpha-IFN), gamma-interferon (gamma-IFN) or interleukin-2
             (IL-2)

          -  Media opacity that precludes visualization of the fundus in all eyes meeting
             eligibility criteria

          -  Active medical problems, including drug or alcohol abuse, that are considered
             sufficient to hinder compliance with treatment or follow up procedures

          -  Retinal detachment, not scheduled for surgical repair, in all eyes meeting other
             eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>MSL-109 adjuvant therapy for cytomegalovirus retinitis in patients with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome: the Monoclonal Antibody Cytomegalovirus Retinitis Trial. The Studies of Ocular Complications of AIDS Research Group. AIDS Clinical Trials Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1997 Dec;115(12):1528-36. Erratum in: Arch Ophthalmol 1998 Mar;116(3):296.</citation>
    <PMID>9400786</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jabs DA, Gilpin AM, Min YI, Erice A, Kempen JH, Quinn TC; Studies of Ocular Complications of AIDS Research Group. HIV and cytomegalovirus viral load and clinical outcomes in AIDS and cytomegalovirus retinitis patients: Monoclonal Antibody Cytomegalovirus Retinitis Trial. AIDS. 2002 Apr 12;16(6):877-87.</citation>
    <PMID>11919489</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Davidson M, Min YI, Holbrook JT, Van Natta M, Quinn TC, Murphy RL, Welch W, Jabs DA, Meinert CL; Studies of Ocular Complications of AIDS Research Group. Influence of filgrastim (granulocyte colony-stimulating factor) on human immunodeficiency virus type 1 RNA in patients with cytomegalovirus retinitis. J Infect Dis. 2002 Oct 1;186(7):1013-8. Epub 2002 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>12232843</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gilpin AM, Holbrook JT, Jabs DA, Meinert CL; Studies of Ocular Complications of AIDS Research Group. Data and safety monitoring board deliberations resulting in the early termination of the Monoclonal Antibody Cytomegalovirus Retinitis Trial. Control Clin Trials. 2003 Feb;24(1):92-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12559647</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 14, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 23, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <firstreceived_results_date>June 12, 2015</firstreceived_results_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results are available for this study                                           -->
</clinical_study>
