<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204373">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>108</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL048631</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Influence of CPB Temperature on CABG Morbidity</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baystate Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baystate Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare three accepted modes of myocardial preservation, warm, tepid, and cold blood
      cardioplegia, coinciding with normothermic (37 degrees centigrade), tepid (32 degrees
      centigrade) and hypothermic (8 to 10 degrees centigrade) cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) to
      define differences in neurologic function in coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      A pilot study of warm versus cold perfusion and preservation was completed in 32 patients
      prior to the ongoing study. The findings of the pilot study showed 53 percent of patients
      had evidence of new neurologic disturbance at postoperative day four. Only the neurologic
      dysfunction could be correlated with warm versus cold perfusion (37.5 percent warm versus 75
      percent cold, P less than 0.05). The changes in neurologic function had abated or clearly
      improved by one month of follow-up, and the distinction in neurologic dysfunction grading
      was no longer apparent between the two groups.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Patients were randomly assigned to cold, tepid, or warm blood cardioplegia, coinciding with
      normothermic, tepid, and hypothermic cardiopulmonary bypass. All patients received a
      standard anesthetic protocol combining narcotic and inhalational anesthesia. Each patient
      entering the study had extensive clinical data collected prospectively incorporating most
      aspects of measurable determinants related to myocardial preservation. Additionally,
      neurologic tests were performed by a blinded neurologist and rated by an objective scoring
      system, the Mathew scale. The studies were performed preoperatively, on the third or fourth
      postoperative day, and at one month following surgery. Hematologic data were measured for
      fibrinolytic potential.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1994</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 1996</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Neurologic Manifestations</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cardiopulmonary bypass</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>heart arrest, induced</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients, referred for elective or urgent coronary revascularization, not having ongoing
        angina instability, requiring three or more bypass grafts, and under 70 years of age.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engelman RM, Pleet AB, Rousou JA, Flack JE 3rd, Deaton DW, Kulshrestha P, Gregory CA, Pekow PS. Does cardiopulmonary bypass temperature correlate with postoperative central nervous system dysfunction? J Card Surg. 1995 Jul;10(4 Suppl):493-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7579848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engelman RM, Pleet AB, Rousou JA, Flack JE 3rd, Deaton DW, Gregory CA, Pekow PS. What is the best perfusion temperature for coronary revascularization? J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 1996 Dec;112(6):1622-32; discussion 1632-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8975854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 11, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurologic Manifestations</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
