<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204436">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>84</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL046959</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's Antioxidant and Folic Acid Cardiovascular Study (WAFACS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>WAFACS</acronym>
  <official_title>Women's Antioxidant and Folic Acid Cardiovascular Study (WAFACS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine if supplements of vitamin C, vitamin E, beta-carotene, and B-vitamins (a
      combination of folic acid, vitamins B6 and B12) reduce risk of major cardiovascular events
      in high risk women with a prior history of atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. The trial
      is a companion to the Women's Health Study (WHS), a primary prevention trial of vitamin E
      and aspirin in a low risk population of women.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Women's Antioxidant and Folic Acid Cardiovascular Study tested the effects of vitamin C
      (500 mg/day), vitamin E (600 IU every other day), and/or beta carotene (50 mg every other
      day) on the risk of major cardiovascular events (a combined outcome of myocardial
      infarction, stroke, coronary revascularization, or cardiovascular death) among 8171 female
      health professionals at increased risk. Participants were 40 years or older with a history
      of cardiovascular disease or 3 or more cardiovascular risk factors and were followed for an
      average duration of 9.4 years, from 1995-1996 to 2005. In 1998, 5442 of these participants
      were further randomized to the B-vitamin intervention (a daily combination pill containing
      folic acid [2.5 mg], vitamin B6 [50 mg], vitamin B12 [1 mg]) and were followed for 7.3
      years, from April 1998 through July 2005.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1993</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular disease</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dietary supplements</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vitamin C</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vitamin E</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>beta-carotene</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>folic acid/Vitamin B6/Vitamin B12</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Women, aged 40 and over, at high risk, with a history of cardiovascular disease or three
        or more coronary heart disease risk factors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>JoAnn Manson</last_name>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manson JE, Gaziano JM, Spelsberg A, Ridker PM, Cook NR, Buring JE, Willett WC, Hennekens CH. A secondary prevention trial of antioxidant vitamins and cardiovascular disease in women. Rationale, design, and methods. The WACS Research Group. Ann Epidemiol. 1995 Jul;5(4):261-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8520707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mason PJ, Manson JE, Sesso HD, Albert CM, Chown MJ, Cook NR, Greenland P, Ridker PM, Glynn RJ. Blood pressure and risk of secondary cardiovascular events in women: the Women's Antioxidant Cardiovascular Study (WACS). Circulation. 2004 Apr 6;109(13):1623-9. Epub 2004 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>15023883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bassuk SS, Albert CM, Cook NR, Zaharris E, MacFadyen JG, Danielson E, Van Denburgh M, Buring JE, Manson JE. The Women's Antioxidant Cardiovascular Study: design and baseline characteristics of participants. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2004 Jan-Feb;13(1):99-117.</citation>
    <PMID>15006283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cook NR, Albert CM, Gaziano JM, Zaharris E, MacFadyen J, Danielson E, Buring JE, Manson JE. A randomized factorial trial of vitamins C and E and beta carotene in the secondary prevention of cardiovascular events in women: results from the Women's Antioxidant Cardiovascular Study. Arch Intern Med. 2007 Aug 13-27;167(15):1610-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17698683</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zhang SM, Cook NR, Albert CM, Gaziano JM, Buring JE, Manson JE. Effect of combined folic acid, vitamin B6, and vitamin B12 on cancer risk in women: a randomized trial. JAMA. 2008 Nov 5;300(17):2012-21. doi: 10.1001/jama.2008.555.</citation>
    <PMID>18984888</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kang JH, Cook N, Manson J, Buring JE, Albert CM, Grodstein F. A trial of B vitamins and cognitive function among women at high risk of cardiovascular disease. Am J Clin Nutr. 2008 Dec;88(6):1602-10. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.2008.26404.</citation>
    <PMID>19064521</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Albert CM, Cook NR, Gaziano JM, Zaharris E, MacFadyen J, Danielson E, Buring JE, Manson JE. Effect of folic acid and B vitamins on risk of cardiovascular events and total mortality among women at high risk for cardiovascular disease: a randomized trial. JAMA. 2008 May 7;299(17):2027-36. doi: 10.1001/jama.299.17.2027.</citation>
    <PMID>18460663</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Song Y, Cook NR, Albert CM, Van Denburgh M, Manson JE. Effects of vitamins C and E and beta-carotene on the risk of type 2 diabetes in women at high risk of cardiovascular disease: a randomized controlled trial. Am J Clin Nutr. 2009 Aug;90(2):429-37. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.2009.27491. Epub 2009 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19491386</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Song Y, Cook NR, Albert CM, Van Denburgh M, Manson JE. Effect of homocysteine-lowering treatment with folic Acid and B vitamins on risk of type 2 diabetes in women: a randomized, controlled trial. Diabetes. 2009 Aug;58(8):1921-8. doi: 10.2337/db09-0087. Epub 2009 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19491213</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lin J, Cook NR, Albert C, Zaharris E, Gaziano JM, Van Denburgh M, Buring JE, Manson JE. Vitamins C and E and beta carotene supplementation and cancer risk: a randomized controlled trial. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2009 Jan 7;101(1):14-23. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djn438. Epub 2008 Dec 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19116389</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kang JH, Cook NR, Manson JE, Buring JE, Albert CM, Grodstein F. Vitamin E, vitamin C, beta carotene, and cognitive function among women with or at risk of cardiovascular disease: The Women's Antioxidant and Cardiovascular Study. Circulation. 2009 Jun 2;119(21):2772-80. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.816900. Epub 2009 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>19451353</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Christen WG, Glynn RJ, Chew EY, Albert CM, Manson JE. Folic acid, pyridoxine, and cyanocobalamin combination treatment and age-related macular degeneration in women: the Women's Antioxidant and Folic Acid Cardiovascular Study. Arch Intern Med. 2009 Feb 23;169(4):335-41. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2008.574.</citation>
    <PMID>19237716</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Song Y, Manson JE, Lee IM, Cook NR, Paul L, Selhub J, Giovannucci E, Zhang SM. Effect of combined folic acid, vitamin B(6), and vitamin B(12) on colorectal adenoma. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2012 Oct 17;104(20):1562-75. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djs370. Epub 2012 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23066166</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 10, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>JoAnn E. Manson, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Preventive Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital; Professor of Medicine and the Michael and Lee Bell Professor of Women's Health, Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antioxidants</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Beta Carotene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B 12</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B Complex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
