<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204432">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>88</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pathways</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To implement a culturally appropriate school-based, multicenter, randomized trial that
      promotes healthful eating behaviors and increases physical activity to prevent obesity in
      pre-adolescent upper elementary American Indian students.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      The American Indian population, including American Indians and Alaska Natives, totals nearly
      1.5 million from over 500 tribes and nearly 300 reservations and Alaska Native villages.
      Earlier in this century, heart disease was rarely noted in American Indians, but in the past
      decade, cardiovascular disease has become the leading cause of death in American Indians.
      Several factors may be responsible for this increase: a decreasing incidence of infectious
      disease, an increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus, and an increasing incidence of
      obesity. Previous research on non-Indian populations indicates that obesity is an
      independent risk factor for cardiovascular disease and that it is associated with increases
      in other cardiovascular disease risk factors such as high blood pressure, diabetes, and low
      high density lipoprotein cholesterol levels. The high prevalence of obesity among American
      Indians, coupled with its role as a risk factor for hypertension, coronary heart disease,
      and diabetes, suggests that a reduction in the average weight of young American Indians
      would improve their health. Reduction of the prevalence of obesity in American Indians has
      been designated as a goal for improving the health of this minority population and reducing
      health disparities in our nation.

      The successful 4-1/2 year feasibility study was followed by the full-scale randomized trial
      involving 1,700 American Indian elementary schoolchildren. Schools were the unit of
      randomization.

      The initiative was developed as a result of consultations with the NHLBI Ad Hoc Committee on
      Minority Populations, the Conference on Obesity and Cardiovascular Disease in Minority
      Populations, and the Indian Health Service. The need for the study was reinforced by the
      preliminary data from the Strong Heart Study confirming the high prevalence of obesity in
      American Indians. The initiative was approved by the Clinical Applications and Prevention
      Advisory Committee in February 1992 and given concept clearance by the National Heart, Lung,
      and Blood Advisory Council in May 1992.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The Feasibility Phase of the trial was completed in 1995. The organizational structure has
      been established, validation studies to determine an endpoint and formative assessment of
      the tribe communities was completed. Intervention including classroom curriculum, food
      service, physical activity family component and for the measurement methods including
      obesity, physical activity, diet intake, knowledge, attitudes and behavior, and process
      evaluation were completed.

      The full-scale trial started in September 1996. The primary aim was to test the effectivenes
      of a culturally appropriate school-based intervention that promoted increased physical
      activity and healthful eating behaviors to prevent obesity in American Indian upper
      elementary school children. The primary outcome was percent body fat after three years of
      intervention. The major hypothesis was that intervention would result in an absolute
      difference of 3 percent body fat between the control and intervention schools. All students
      enrolled in the second grade in the participating schools during Spring, 1997 participated
      in the baseline survey. Baseline measurements were performed at the end of second grade so
      that the intervention could begin at the start of third grade. The intervention lasted for
      three years. A single cohort of children progressed through third, fourth, and fifth grades.
      Schools were the unit of randomization. Forty-one schools in four centers were stratified
      within each field center on median percent body fat (PBF) at the end of second grade using
      data from the baseline measurement. Schools within a field center were then ranked on median
      PBF. Once stratified, the coordinating center randomly assigned half the schools within each
      stratum to intervention (21) and half to control (20).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1993</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Sedentary Behaviors</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>exercise</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diet</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Cohort of pre-adolescent American Indian boys and girls followed in grades 3-5.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>H. Stevens</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prevention of obesity in American Indian children: the Pathways study. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):745S-824S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195596</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caballero B: Introduction. Am J Clin Nutr, 69: 745S-746S, 1999.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Story M, Evans M, Fabsitz RR, Clay TE, Holy Rock B, Broussard B. The epidemic of obesity in American Indian communities and the need for childhood obesity-prevention programs. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):747S-754S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10195597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davis CE, Hunsberger S, Murray DM, Fabsitz RR, Himes JH, Stephenson LK, Caballero B, Skipper B. Design and statistical analysis for the Pathways study. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):760S-763S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lohman TG, Caballero B, Himes JH, Hunsberger S, Reid R, Stewart D, Skipper B. Body composition assessment in American Indian children. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):764S-766S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gittelsohn J, Evans M, Story M, Davis SM, Metcalfe L, Helitzer DL, Clay TE. Multisite formative assessment for the Pathways study to prevent obesity in American Indian schoolchildren. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):767S-772S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stevens J, Cornell CE, Story M, French SA, Levin S, Becenti A, Gittelsohn J, Going SB, Reid R. Development of a questionnaire to assess knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors in American Indian children. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):773S-781S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weber JL, Cunningham-Sabo L, Skipper B, Lytle L, Stevens J, Gittelsohn J, Anliker J, Heller K, Pablo JL. Portion-size estimation training in second- and third-grade American Indian children. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):782S-787S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Going SB, Levin S, Harrell J, Stewart D, Kushi L, Cornell CE, Hunsberger S, Corbin C, Sallis J. Physical activity assessment in American Indian schoolchildren in the Pathways study. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):788S-795S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davis SM, Going SB, Helitzer DL, Teufel NI, Snyder P, Gittelsohn J, Metcalfe L, Arviso V, Evans M, Smyth M, Brice R, Altaha J. Pathways: a culturally appropriate obesity-prevention program for American Indian schoolchildren. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):796S-802S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snyder P, Anliker J, Cunningham-Sabo L, Dixon LB, Altaha J, Chamberlain A, Davis S, Evans M, Hurley J, Weber JL. The Pathways study: a model for lowering the fat in school meals. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):810S-815S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Helitzer DL, Davis SM, Gittelsohn J, Going SB, Murray DM, Snyder P, Steckler AB. Process evaluation in a multisite, primary obesity-prevention trial in American Indian schoolchildren. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):816S-824S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stevens J, Story M, Becenti A, French SA, Gittelsohn J, Going SB, Juhaeri, Levin S, Murray DM. Weight-related attitudes and behaviors in fourth grade American Indian children. Obes Res. 1999 Jan;7(1):34-42.</citation>
    <PMID>10023728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gittelsohn J, Evans M, Helitzer D, Anliker J, Story M, Metcalfe L, Davis S, Iron Cloud P. Formative research in a school-based obesity prevention program for Native American school children (Pathways). Health Educ Res. 1998 Jun;13(2):251-65.</citation>
    <PMID>10181023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koehler KM, Cunningham-Sabo L, Lambert LC, McCalman R, Skipper BJ, Davis SM. Assessing food selection in a health promotion program: validation of a brief instrument for American Indian children in the southwest United States. J Am Diet Assoc. 2000 Feb;100(2):205-11.</citation>
    <PMID>10670393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teufel NI, Perry CL, Story M, Flint-Wagner HG, Levin S, Clay TE, Davis SM, Gittelsohn J, Altaha J, Pablo JL. Pathways family intervention for third-grade American Indian children. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):803S-809S.</citation>
    <PMID>10195606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davis SM, Reid R. Practicing participatory research in American Indian communities. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999 Apr;69(4 Suppl):755S-759S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10195598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Story M, Stevens J, Evans M, Cornell CE, Juhaeri, Gittelsohn J, Going SB, Clay TE, Murray DM. Weight loss attempts and attitudes toward body size, eating, and physical activity in American Indian children: relationship to weight status and gender. Obes Res. 2001 Jun;9(6):356-63.</citation>
    <PMID>11399782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lohman TG, Caballero B, Himes JH, Davis CE, Stewart D, Houtkooper L, Going SB, Hunsberger S, Weber JL, Reid R, Stephenson L. Estimation of body fat from anthropometry and bioelectrical impedance in Native American children. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 2000 Aug;24(8):982-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10951536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson JL, Davis SM, Gittelsohn J, Going S, Becenti A, Metcalfe L, Stone E, Harnack L, Ring K. Patterns of physical activity among American Indian children: an assessment of barriers and support. J Community Health. 2001 Dec;26(6):423-45.</citation>
    <PMID>11759094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunsberger S, Murray D, Davis CE, Fabsitz RR. Imputation strategies for missing data in a school-based multi-centre study: the Pathways study. Stat Med. 2001 Jan 30;20(2):305-16.</citation>
    <PMID>11169604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Story M, Snyder P, Anliker J, Cunningham-Sabo L, Weber JL, Platero H, Stone EJ. Nutrient content of school meals in elementary schools on American Indian reservations. J Am Diet Assoc. 2002 Feb;102(2):253-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11846122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lytle LA, Dixon LB, Cunningham-Sabo L, Evans M, Gittelsohn J, Hurley J, Snyder P, Stevens J, Weber J, Anliker J, Heller K, Story M. Dietary intakes of Native American children: findings from the pathways feasibility study. J Am Diet Assoc. 2002 Apr;102(4):555-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11985417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caballero B, Clay T, Davis SM, Ethelbah B, Rock BH, Lohman T, Norman J, Story M, Stone EJ, Stephenson L, Stevens J; Pathways Study Research Group. Pathways: a school-based, randomized controlled trial for the prevention of obesity in American Indian schoolchildren. Am J Clin Nutr. 2003 Nov;78(5):1030-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14594792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caballero B, Himes JH, Lohman T, Davis SM, Stevens J, Evans M, Going S, Pablo J; Pathways Study Research Group. Body composition and overweight prevalence in 1704 schoolchildren from 7 American Indian communities. Am J Clin Nutr. 2003 Aug;78(2):308-12.</citation>
    <PMID>12885714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Story M, Snyder MP, Anliker J, Weber JL, Cunningham-Sabo L, Stone EJ, Chamberlain A, Ethelbah B, Suchindran C, Ring K. Changes in the nutrient content of school lunches: results from the Pathways study. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S35-45.</citation>
    <PMID>14636807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gittelsohn J, Davis SM, Steckler A, Ethelbah B, Clay T, Metcalfe L, Rock BH. Pathways: lessons learned and future directions for school-based interventions among American Indians. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S107-12.</citation>
    <PMID>14636815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gittelsohn J, Merkle S, Story M, Stone EJ, Steckler A, Noel J, Davis S, Martin CJ, Ethelbah B. School climate and implementation of the Pathways study. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S97-106.</citation>
    <PMID>14636814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lohman T, Thompson J, Going S, Himes JH, Caballero B, Norman J, Cano S, Ring K. Indices of changes in adiposity in American Indian children. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S91-6.</citation>
    <PMID>14636813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steckler A, Ethelbah B, Martin CJ, Stewart D, Pardilla M, Gittelsohn J, Stone E, Fenn D, Smyth M, Vu M. Pathways process evaluation results: a school-based prevention trial to promote healthful diet and physical activity in American Indian third, fourth, and fifth grade students. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S80-90.</citation>
    <PMID>14636812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stevens J, Story M, Ring K, Murray DM, Cornell CE, Juhaeri, Gittelsohn J. The impact of the Pathways intervention on psychosocial variables related to diet and physical activity in American Indian schoolchildren. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S70-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14636811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Going S, Thompson J, Cano S, Stewart D, Stone E, Harnack L, Hastings C, Norman J, Corbin C. The effects of the Pathways Obesity Prevention Program on physical activity in American Indian children. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S62-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14636810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Himes JH, Ring K, Gittelsohn J, Cunningham-Sabo L, Weber J, Thompson J, Harnack L, Suchindran C. Impact of the Pathways intervention on dietary intakes of American Indian schoolchildren. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S55-61.</citation>
    <PMID>14636809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gunnarsson LG, Bodin L, Söderfeldt B, Axelson O. A case-control study of motor neurone disease: its relation to heritability, and occupational exposures, particularly to solvents. Br J Ind Med. 1992 Nov;49(11):791-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1463680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stone EJ, Norman JE, Davis SM, Stewart D, Clay TE, Caballero B, Lohman TG, Murray DM. Design, implementation, and quality control in the Pathways American-Indian multicenter trial. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S13-23.</citation>
    <PMID>14636805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Story M, Stevens J, Himes J, Stone E, Rock BH, Ethelbah B, Davis S. Obesity in American-Indian children: prevalence, consequences, and prevention. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S3-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14636804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cunningham-Sabo L, Snyder MP, Anliker J, Thompson J, Weber JL, Thomas O, Ring K, Stewart D, Platero H, Nielsen L. Impact of the Pathways food service intervention on breakfast served in American-Indian schools. Prev Med. 2003 Dec;37(6 Pt 2):S46-54.</citation>
    <PMID>14636808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weber JL, Lytle L, Gittelsohn J, Cunningham-Sabo L, Heller K, Anliker JA, Stevens J, Hurley J, Ring K. Validity of self-reported dietary intake at school meals by American Indian children: the Pathways Study. J Am Diet Assoc. 2004 May;104(5):746-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15127059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 3, 2006</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
