<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204480">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000497</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01HL037854</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000497</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dietary Intervention Study for Hypertension (DISH)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Mississippi Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Mississippi Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this multicenter cooperative clinical trial was to determine if
      dietary modification would enable drug controlled hypertensive patients to remain at 'goal
      blood pressures' after antihypertensive medication was withdrawn. The proposal made use of
      the HDFP hypertensive population who had five years of treatment for their hypertension.
      Additionally, the group of investigators proposed to determine if dietary treatment would
      permit patients not previously adequately controlled under the HDFP program to achieve
      normalization of blood pressure with a combination of dietary modification and drug
      treatment. The study also proposed to search for predictors (i.e., levels of hormonal agents
      such as plasma renin activity) of responsiveness to dietary manipulation among the
      hypertensive population as well as to identify psychological attributes that might be of
      importance in managing these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      The background against which the proposal was made had been developed from the combined
      information of the Veterans Administration Cooperative Study and the Hypertension Detection
      and Follow-up Study. Data from both these studies clearly established the importance of
      reducing sodium content by means of diuretic administration as a mainstay of the treatment
      of elevated blood pressure. The risks of the lifetime of treatment were undefined, but the
      cost of indefinite treatment of high blood pressure was sufficiently high to stimulate
      careful examination of alternative modes of management of such patients. The demonstrations
      by Parijs and others that moderate reduction in sodium intake led to improved management of
      hypertension and data suggesting that increased potassium intake may enhance this blood
      pressure lowering effect associated with sodium restriction was cited by the investigators
      as a basis for the trial. Any additional data regarding modest sodium restriction and
      potassium ingestion would have impact on utilizing such therapy in preventing hypertension
      and as adjunctive therapy.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The study was intended to take advantage of the availability of patients at the three
      centers at the completion of the Hypertension Detection and Follow-up Program Study. These
      patients were enrolled as 'stepped-care' participants and had been treated with
      antihypertensive drugs for at least five years. The main objective of the study was to
      determine the contribution of dietary modification to maintenance of normal blood pressure
      after withdrawal of medication. Two types of diet change were followed: 1) reduction of
      sodium intake coupled with increased potassium intake; and 2) reduction of weight in the
      subgroups of patients that were obese.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1980</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1994</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diet, sodium-restricted</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diet, reducing</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women with hypertension. Diastolic blood pressure equal to or above 95 mm Hg and
        90 mm Hg, respectively for home and clinic readings.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Herbert Langford</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Mississippi Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wassertheil-Smoller S, Langford HG, Blaufox, MD, et al: Rate of Hypertension Return After Withdrawal of Prolonged Antihypertensive Therapy. Clin Sci, 63: 423S-525S (Supp 8), 1982.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wassertheil-Smoller, Langford HG, Blaufox MD, Oberman A, Hawkins M. Diuretics and salt restriction in blood pressure control. Curr Concepts Nutr. 1983;12:175-89. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6342972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langford HG, Blaufox, MD, Oberman A, et al: Effect of Weight Loss on the Return of Hypertension After Withdrawal of Prolonged Antihypertensive Therapy. Nutritional Prevention of Cardiovascular Disease, 301-315, 1984.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wing RR, Caggiula AW, Nowalk MP, Koeske R, Lee S, Langford H. Dietary approaches to the reduction of blood pressure: the independence of weight and sodium/potassium interventions. Prev Med. 1984 May;13(3):233-44.</citation>
    <PMID>6494106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langford HG, Blaufox MD, Oberman A, Hawkins CM, Curb JD, Cutter GR, Wassertheil-Smoller S, Pressel S, Babcock C, Abernethy JD, et al. Dietary therapy slows the return of hypertension after stopping prolonged medication. JAMA. 1985 Feb 1;253(5):657-64.</citation>
    <PMID>3881608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langford HG, Schlundt D, Levine K. Sodium restriction in hypertension. Compr Ther. 1984 Sep;10(9):6-11.</citation>
    <PMID>6488753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2000</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 14, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
