<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204438">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000539</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>82</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000539</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Arterial Disease Multifactorial Intervention Trial (ADMIT)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate, in asymptomatic and symptomatic participants with peripheral arterial disease,
      the feasibility of recruitment and adherence, efficacy and safety of HDL-C raising along
      with effective control of LDL-C levels, antioxidant therapy, antithrombotic therapy, and
      their combinations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Multiple mechanisms are involved in the deposition of LDL-C into the arterial wall, and the
      prevention of such deposition as well as the removal of the LDL-particles. Further, there
      remain questions regarding what causes an existing plaque that has been stable for a long
      period of time to become occlusive or ulcerating and what may prevent it from doing so.
      Prevention and treatment are almost certain to become multifaceted and more complex when
      using several complementary interventions or preventive measures concomitantly.

      Multifactorial prevention and treatment may be particularly useful in people with peripheral
      arterial disease. PAD as manifested by intermittent claudication affects about 0.5 to 1.0
      percent of individuals above age 35, with a twofold predominance in men. There is a
      strikingly increased incidence with age in both sexes, particularly in those above age 50.
      Mortality in patients with intermittent claudication has been shown to be six times higher
      than in other people of similar age and gender. The excess in mortality is primarily due to
      a ninefold increase in cardiovascular disease (CVD) deaths. Those who have asymptomatic but
      measurable PAD (two to two-and-a-half times as many as have intermittent claudication), have
      relative risks of about 3 and 4 for total and CVD mortality, respectively. Therefore,
      interventions that prevent the development or progression of atherosclerotic disease or
      reduce arterial thrombosis should reduce mortality and morbidity due to myocardial
      infarction and stroke while favorably affecting the morbidity directly associated with PAD.

      The National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) has included peripheral vascular disease
      (PVD) in its guidelines as a risk factor in the Classification and Decision for Treatment
      Algorithm. This means that patients who have PVD and elevated LDL-C and one other risk
      factor such as male gender, family history, cigarette smoking, or hypertension, should have
      appropriate dietary intervention followed by drug therapy as needed. Even with the
      guidelines in place since the end of 1987, a survey of PVD patients referred to a major
      medical center clinic found that very few patients were on lipid lowering therapy, either
      diet or drug. The reason for the primary care community not modifying lipids in these high
      risk patients may be related to lack of studies demonstrating benefit of lipid modification
      in those who have PVD. It is anticipated that many patients with PAD will require treatment
      for elevated LDL-C. It is not as clear whether interventions aimed at raising HDL-C will
      result in a slowing of progression of atherosclerosis in this population.

      Platelets have been shown to have a key role in the development of occlusive atherosclerosis
      and thrombosis related to coronary heart disease. Inhibition of platelet function has been
      postulated to slow progression of atherosclerosis; specifically, aspirin has been
      demonstrated to reduce lipoprotein deposition in the arterial wall of nonhuman primates.
      This deposition is even further reduced by the addition of a lipid lowering regimen to the
      antiplatelet regimen. It remains unclear whether mini-dose, less intense anticoagulation is
      the most appropriate antithrombotic therapy in people with PAD who are also receiving lipid
      modifying agents.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Patients were randomized to a control arm or to one of three treatment arms, including a
      lipid modification arm, an antioxidant arm, and an antithrombotic arm. Patients in the lipid
      modification arm were randomized to placebo or treated with nicotinic acid to increase HDL
      while lowering LDL levels equally with the hydroxymethylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase
      inhibitor pravastatin as needed in the intervention and control groups. Patients in the
      antioxidant arm were assigned to daily doses of 24 mg. of beta-carotene, 800 IU of vitamin
      E, and 1.0 g of vitamin C or to placebo. Patients in the antithrombotic arm received 2
      mg/day of active or placebo warfarin taken daily until the fifth follow-up visit. Patients
      were followed every six weeks after entry for one year of follow-up. The primary endpoint of
      the study was the efficacy and safety of HDL-C raising along with effective control of LDL-C
      levels, antioxidant therapy, antithrombotic therapy, and their combinations. The secondary
      endpoints were to determine the efficacy of the HDL-C raising arm to achieve an increase in
      HDL-C in the treatment group while also obtaining equivalent reductions in LDL-C in the
      treatment and control groups, to assess the dose-response of niacin on HDL-C raising, to
      determine if the combination of low-dose warfarin plus aspirin versus aspirin alone had the
      expected impact on the hemostatic system, to determine if combination antioxidant therapy
      (vitamins E and C and beta carotene) led to changes in biomarkers for antioxidants, and to
      determine the interaction of the lipid altering strategy with antioxidants for effects on
      biomarkers for antioxidants. Screening began August 1, 1993, randomization began December 1,
      1993 and ended December 31, 1994 with a total of 468 patients enrolled. Support for the
      trial ended in September 1995. Data analysis continues through March 31, 1999 under contract
      N01HC35124.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1992</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 1999</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <condition>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>niacin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pravastatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>beta-carotene</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vitamin E</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dietary supplements</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vitamin C</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>warfarin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women with symptomatic or asymptomatic peripheral arterial disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathryn Davis</last_name>
    <affiliation>Statistics and Epidemiology Research Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Egan DA, Garg R, Wilt TJ, Pettinger MB, Davis KB, Crouse J, Herd JA, Hunninghake DB, Sheps DS, Kostis JB, Probstfield J, Waclawiw MA, Applegate W, Elam MB. Rationale and design of the Arterial Disease Multiple Intervention Trial (ADMIT) pilot study. Am J Cardiol. 1999 Feb 15;83(4):569-75.</citation>
    <PMID>10073863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elam MB, Hunninghake DB, Davis KB, Garg R, Johnson C, Egan D, Kostis JB, Sheps DS, Brinton EA. Effect of niacin on lipid and lipoprotein levels and glycemic control in patients with diabetes and peripheral arterial disease: the ADMIT study: A randomized trial. Arterial Disease Multiple Intervention Trial. JAMA. 2000 Sep 13;284(10):1263-70.</citation>
    <PMID>10979113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garg R, Elam MB, Crouse JR 3rd, Davis KB, Kennedy JW, Egan D, Herd JA, Hunninghake DB, Johnson WC, Kostis JB, Sheps DS, Applegate WB. Effective and safe modification of multiple atherosclerotic risk factors in patients with peripheral arterial disease. Am Heart J. 2000 Nov;140(5):792-803.</citation>
    <PMID>11054628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chesney CM, Elam MB, Herd JA, Davis KB, Garg R, Hunninghake D, Kennedy JW, Applegate WB. Effect of niacin, warfarin, and antioxidant therapy on coagulation parameters in patients with peripheral arterial disease in the Arterial Disease Multiple Intervention Trial (ADMIT). Am Heart J. 2000 Oct;140(4):631-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11011338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2006</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2006</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 27, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Beta Carotene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
