<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204558">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P60 AR20582 Substudy EEHSR4</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P60AR020582</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NIAMS-025</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Psychosocial Treatment for Acute Low Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Psychosocial Intervention for Acute Low Back Pain (ALBP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute low back pain (severe pain that comes on suddenly and lasts a relatively short time)
      is very common in the United States, and accounts for substantial illness, functional
      limitations, pain, and health care costs. This study looks at whether a program designed to
      improve self-efficacy (a person's belief in his or her ability to reach a goal, such as
      managing one's own disease) and social support improves the health status of people with
      acute low back pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute low back pain (ALBP) is very prevalent in the United States, accounting for
      substantial morbidity, functional limitations, pain, and health care costs. Psychosocial
      interventions that target improved symptom control and patient functioning have the
      potential to improve the outcomes of patients with ALBP. This study evaluates a psychosocial
      intervention designed to enhance self-efficacy and social support for patients with ALBP.

      In this randomized, controlled trial, we will randomize eligible patients with ALBP to
      receive the intervention or usual care. The intervention program consists of: (1) patient
      education regarding ALBP; (2) explanations and rationales, in layperson's terms, of
      diagnostic and treatment options for ALBP; (3) discussions regarding the management of
      negative affect (i.e., depression, anger, fear, hostility, anxiety); (4) methods to involve
      social support systems; and (5) strategies to involve the primary care physician to
      reinforce patients' behaviors and progress. We will follow patients for 12 months and assess
      outcomes at 3 and 12 months.

      Primary outcomes are health-related quality of life (i.e., functional status, role function,
      back pain symptoms) and patient satisfaction with care. Secondary outcomes include health
      care use, direct health care costs, self-efficacy, and social support. We will also estimate
      the cost-effectiveness of the intervention.

      We will conduct this investigation among socioeconomically vulnerable patients with ALBP, a
      group that shoulders a disproportionate burden of disability and morbidity from
      musculoskeletal conditions and comorbid medical conditions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1977</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 2001</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <enrollment>211</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Low Back Pain</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychosocial intervention</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute low back pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic back pain (including surgery)

          -  Disability claim for back pain

          -  Nursing home resident

          -  Severe impairment in hearing, vision, or speech

          -  Unable to speak English

          -  Severe comorbidity

          -  Unable to contact by phone

          -  Excluded by primary care physician
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morris Weinberger, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Damush TM, Weinberger M, Clark DO, Tierney WM, Rao JK, Perkins SM, Verel K. Acute low back pain self-management intervention for urban primary care patients: rationale, design, and predictors of participation. Arthritis Rheum. 2002 Aug;47(4):372-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12209482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Damush TM, Weinberger M, Perkins SM, Rao JK, Tierney WM, Qi R, Clark DO. Randomized trial of a self-management program for primary care patients with acute low back pain: short-term effects. Arthritis Rheum. 2003 Apr 15;49(2):179-86.</citation>
    <PMID>12687508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Damush TM, Weinberger M, Tierney WM, Rao J, Clark DO, Adams K, Perkins S, &amp; Emsley C. A comparison between older and younger adults with acute low back pain on functional status and self-management. Poster presented at the annual meeting of the Gerontological Society of America, San Francisco, CA. The Gerontologist. 1999;39:S571.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Damush TM, Weinberger M, Perkins SM, Rao JK, Tierney WM, Qi R, Clark DO. The long-term effects of a self-management program for inner-city primary care patients with acute low back pain. Arch Intern Med. 2003 Nov 24;163(21):2632-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14638564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 1999</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 3, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>OA</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient education</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute low back pain (ALBP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Social support systems</keyword>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
