<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="204193">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 16, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000787</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HATS PROSPECTIVE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000787</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heterosexual HIV Transmission Study (HATS). Prospective Cohort Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Heterosexual HIV Transmission Study (HATS). Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY: To identify factors associated with risk of HIV infection through heterosexual
      activity among urban, inner-city women.

      SECONDARY: To identify correlates of high-risk behaviors in order to provide a basis for
      future intervention studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      At baseline and at 6-month intervals, participants are interviewed about their sexual
      behavior, drug and alcohol-related behaviors, and recent medical history, and are given a
      psychosocial assessment. They also undergo a physical exam, including pelvic exam and
      colposcopy, and have blood and urine specimens collected for HIV testing, drug screening,
      and STD evaluation. Additionally, participants are given pre- and post-test counseling and
      education, including information about social services. They are provided with basic
      gynecological care and either treatment or referral for medical problems.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <enrollment>1000</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre- and post-test counseling</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Participants must meet the following criteria:

          -  HIV-negative, sexually active women living in social and sexual proximity to men at
             high risk for acquiring HIV infection.

          -  Able to speak English, Spanish, or Creole.

          -  Living in the geographic area surrounding Kings County Hospital in Brooklyn, New
             York. (Hospital-based and community-based recruitment sites will be utilized.)

        Personal history of parenteral drug use by self-report or urine test. Heterosexual contact
        with men at high risk for HIV infection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY / Health Sciences Ctr at Brooklyn</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skurnick J, Bromberg J, Cordell J, Foley M, Wang W, Louria D. Change in couples' sexual activity after knowledge of HIV discordance: a report from the heterosexual HIV transmission study (HATS). Int Conf AIDS. 1992 Jul 19-24;8(2):C273 (abstract no PoC 4170)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skurnick J, Bromberg J, Grijalva K, Cordell J, Louria D, Monto A, Weiss S. Behavior changes in heterosexual couples discordant for HIV: a report from the heterosexual HIV transmission study (HATS). Int Conf AIDS. 1991 Jun 16-21;7(2):319 (abstract no WC3094)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Padian N, Bromberg J, O'Brien T, Vranizan K, Cordell J, Louria D, Van-Devanter N, Landesman S. Smoking and bleeding from trauma during sex: risks for heterosexual transmission of HIV. The HATS/CDC Research Group. Int Conf AIDS. 1993 Jun 6-11;9(2):648 (abstract no PO-C02-2588)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wan J, Bromberg J, Cornell RG, Skurnick J, Cordell J, Vermund S. Generalized additive models for paired covariates in an HIV discordant couples study: a report from The Heterosexual HIV Transmission Study (HATS). Int Conf AIDS. 1992 Jul 19-24;8(3):193 (abstract no PuC 8243)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bromberg J, Wan J, Cornell RG, Grijalva K, Cordell J, Kelly P, Landesman S. Entry criteria bias in studies of high-risk individuals: a report from the heterosexual HIV transmission study (HATS). Int Conf AIDS. 1992 Jul 19-24;8(2):C371 (abstract no PoC 4773)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bromberg J, Maher J, Wang W, Grijalva K, Cordell J. Within couple disagreement on condom use: a report from the heterosexual HIV transmission study (HATS/CDC). Int Conf AIDS. 1993 Jun 6-11;9(2):774 (abstract no PO-C33-3345)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sogolow ED, Des Jarlais D, Landesman SH, Kelly P, Sampson-Lee G, Cordell J, Cornell R. The experience of participating in a cohort study of HIV transmission: a report from The Heterosexual HIV Transmission Study (HATS). Int Conf AIDS. 1992 Jul 19-24;8(3):189 (abstract no PuC 8216)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cornell RG, Bromberg J, Grijalva K, Kelly P, Cordell J. Effects of changing recruitment patterns on risk factor estimates: a report from the heterosexual HIV transmission study (HATS). Int Conf AIDS. 1992 Jul 19-24;8(2):C324 (abstract no PoC 4477)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strug D, Des Jarlais D, Sogolow E, Handte J, Bromberg J, Cornell R, Cordell J, Landesman S. Types of sexual partner relationships and condom use among women in Brooklyn: a report from the heterosexual HIV transmission study (HATS). Int Conf AIDS. 1991 Jun 16-21;7(2):324 (abstract no WC3112)</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2003</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 23, 2005</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 2, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Sex Behavior</keyword>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
